<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Utrum horum, or, God's ways of disposing of kingdoms and some clergy-men's ways of disposing of them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08259495</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08259495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 767:37, 1242:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Utrum horum, or, God's ways of disposing of kingdoms and some clergy-men's ways of disposing of them.</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, William, 1627-1717.</author>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by BM to William Henry, Prince of Orange.  Cf. BM, v. 258, col. 49.</note>
                  <note>Originally attributed by Wing to William Lloyd, probably on the basis of Lloyd's work entitled: A discourse of God's ways of disposing of kingdoms ...  Wing (2nd ed.) cancels number L2719.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Entry for L2719 cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sovereignty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:1"/>
            <p>GOD's WAYS OF <hi>Diſpoſing Kingdoms;</hi> AND Some CLERGY-MEN'S Ways, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vtrum horum;</hi> OR, GOD's WAYS OF Diſpoſing of KINGDOMS: AND Some CLERGY-MEN's Ways OF Diſpoſing of THEM.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Who is blind, but my ſervant? or deaf as my meſſenger that I ſent?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 42.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Prophets propheſie lies in my name, neither have I commanded them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpake unto them: They propheſie unto you a falſe viſion, and divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a thing of nought, and the deceit of their heart,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 14.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>O ye hypocrites, ye can diſcern the face of the sky, and can ye not diſcern the ſigns of the times?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 16.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxfords-Arms</hi> Inn, <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is the General ſenſe of Mankind, That Diſcourſes upon any Particular Government, ought to be grounded upon the Laws and Conſtitution of that Government: And it is a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſo clear in it ſelf, that applied to any other thing whatſoever, the contrary will appear ridiculous. No man that were to build a Ship, would conſult the Commentators upon the Book of <hi>Geneſis</hi> for the Fabrick and Dimenſions of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark. Nor is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple made the Pattern of our Churches. Nor are the Laws of the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerv'd by any Chriſtian Kingdom or State. And yet ſome late Divines, in their Diſcourſes upon our Preſent Government, and the Settlement of the Nation under Their Majeſties, and the Revolution that brought it about, do not confine themſelves to <hi>our Laws, and Ancient Government,</hi> but broach Opinions of their own, or other Mens Invention, pretended to be grounded upon Scripture or Reaſon, to juſtify what has been done; and to perſuade the People of <hi>England,</hi> that 'tis their duty to ſubmit, and to plight their Allegiance to Their Majeſties; or at leaſt that it is lawful for them ſo to do. Whether the Grounds they proceed upon, are conſonant to right Reaſon, the Laws of God, and of this Realm, or are not, is far from the Deſign of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Papers to diſpute. That which is aim'd at, being no more than to preſent the Reader with the Senſe and Judgment of thoſe who acted in the Revolution; and who contributed their Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſettle the Nation after the Late King's withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; with the Senſe and Principles of ſome few Divines amongſt us concerning theſe Matters.</p>
            <p>If the latter run wide from the former, then it is to be feared, that thoſe Gentlemen, who would ſeem to eſpouſe the Intereſt of the Government, by putting Pen to Paper in Defence, or at leaſt in
<pb facs="tcp:41262:4"/>excuſe of it, do it more diſſervice, than if they had forborn the venting their Opinions: For it cannot but weaken a well-eſtabliſh'd Government, to perſuade the People under it, that it ſtands upon another Foundation than really it does; eſpecially when that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is not only contrary to the Sentiments of the Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, as will appear hereafter; but is really a Fiction of ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Heads; and no better than the building of a Caſtle in the Air.</p>
            <p>The Oppoſition will appear in a great meaſure by conſidering theſe few Particulars.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs, the then Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> declared, That his <hi>Expedition was intended for no other Deſign, but to have a Free and Lawful Parliament Aſſembled, for doing all things which the Two Houſes ſhould find neceſſary for the Peace, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Safety of the Nation. To which Parliament he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred all things relating to the Succeſſion: and promiſed to concur in every thing, that a Free and Lawful Parliament ſhould determine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They tell us of <hi>Sovereign Princes, Succeſſes in Juſt Wars,</hi> and <hi>Appeals to God.</hi> Whereas the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was not actually a <hi>Sovereign Prince,</hi> being diſpoſſeſs'd of his <hi>Principality:</hi> Nor made war upon the Nation, or ſo much as upon King <hi>James,</hi> but came over with an Army to enforce the ſitting of a <hi>Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> to which <hi>Parliament</hi> he made his <hi>Appeal,</hi> and not to God; though as a Pious and Chriſtian Prince, he relied on the bleſſing of God for the ſucceſs of his Undertaking, in which he placed his whole, and only Confidence.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs <hi>invited and required all Perſons whatſoever; All the Peers of the Realm, both Spiritual and Temporal; All Lords Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenant, and all Gentlemen, Citizens, and other Commons of all Ranks, to come and aſſiſt him, in order to the executing of his ſaid Deſign, againſt all ſuch as ſhould endeavour to oppoſe him.</hi> And accordingly great numbers actually did, and many more, nay the body of the Nation would, if there had been occaſion. And when the Government was ſetled, Their Majeſties, with the concurrence of both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Enacted, That the Oath appointed by the <hi>Statute of
<pb facs="tcp:41262:4"/>13 Car. II.</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act for ordering the Forces of the ſeveral Counties of this Kingdom;</hi> And alſo ſo much of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration preſcribed in another Act made in the ſame year, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An Act for the Uniformity of Publick Prayers, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. as is expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>declare, That it is not lawful, upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King; and that I do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor that Trayterous Poſition, of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are commiſſioned by him:</hi> Should not from henceforth be required or enjoined.</p>
            <p>But theſe Gentlemen tell us, That notwithſtanding the unreaſonable Cavils of Gainſaying Men,<note place="margin">Hickman.</note> Paſſive Obedience always was, and they hope, always will be, the Doctrine and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> That Kings are the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon Earth, unto whom God has given an immediate delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Authority; whom to obey, is to obey his Ordinance; and whom to reſiſt, is to reſiſt his Power.</p>
            <p>They tell us, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> has been very careful to inſtruct her Children to obey their Princes Laws,<note place="margin">Sherlock.</note> and ſubmit to their Power, and not to reſiſt, tho very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly oppreſt; and that thoſe who renounce theſe Principles, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> That whatever Prince is ſetled in the Throne, is to be obeyed and reverenced as God's Miniſter, and not to be reſiſted. That the Church of <hi>England</hi> condemns all thoſe wicked means by which Changes of Government are made.</p>
            <p>That Subjects have no right to make war without the leave of their Princes; for that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Aſaph.</note> as God has given to Princes the Power of the Sword, ſo he has forbid it to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects under a great penalty; They that take the Sword, ſhall periſh with the Sword.</p>
            <p>When the Lords and Commons met at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> they ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Vacancy</hi> of the Throne upon the Late King's having <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the Fundamental Laws of the Realm, and ſince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas, according to theſe Gentlemens Notions, they ought
<pb facs="tcp:41262:5"/>not to have gone upon a Vacancy, but have recognized the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Title to the Crown, as being already choſen thereunto by God, who had given him ſucceſs in a Juſt War againſt King <hi>James</hi> Tho it would have been a hard task for them to have brought the Queen in at that Door.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Parliament that is now in being, recognized Their Preſent Majeſties to be <hi>Rightful and Lawful</hi> King and Queen of this Realm, <hi>according to the Laws of the ſame.</hi> They ought to have acknowledged him King, as being ſet up by God, who is not bound by Humane Laws; and the Queen, as ſet up by God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knows who, who is not bound by Humane Laws neither: and at the ſame time to have own'd, that this Providence of God in ſetting up the King, and this Providence of God-knows-who, in ſetting up the Queen, does not take away the Legal Right of the Late King; but that he having a Legal Right, may aſſert and vindicate it, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Providence of God, and the Providence of God-knows-who: and that all who are not under any obligation to Their Preſent Majeſties, may lawfully aſſiſt him in order to the recovery of this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right. Tho we, who are under an obligation to Their Preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, are bound to obey them, by reaſon of the Events of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, and of the Providence of God-knows-who.</p>
            <p>Other Inſtances of this kind might be added; and it were a very eaſie matter to word ſome parts of the then Prince's Declaration, the Votes of Parliament, the Inſtrument of Government, and ſome few Laws made ſince the Settlement, as they ought to, and would have been worded, if the Prince, the Two Houſes, and the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had proceded upon theſe Gentlemens Principles. But that I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, becauſe it would ſeem ſcurrilous: I leave it to be the reſult of comparing the two Columes of theſe enſuing Papers.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, here's the Senſe of the Legiſlative Body of the Realm, and of the People of <hi>England,</hi> ſet Cheek by Jowle with the Senſe of a few Gentlemen of the Sacred Order; who would perſuade us that our Government is drop'd out of the Skies, like the Image that fell down from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or as the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts perſuaded <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> that he was the Son of their God, being convinced of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I ſuppoſe, by the Events of Providence, and his Succeſs in a War, Juſt, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41262:5"/>
            <head>God's Ways of Diſpoſing of Kingdoms: AND Some Clergy-mens Ways of Diſpoſing of Them.</head>
            <p>THE Meaſures that were taken in the late King's Reign, for the introducing of Popery and Arbitrary Power, were ſo open and undiſguiſed, That the moſt purblind amongſt us, could not but ſee them; and all Proteſtants, that is, the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the People, were uneaſie under their then preſent Circumſtances, and dreadfully apprehenſive of their future. Inſtead of enumerating the ſeveral Illegal Practices then on foot, to ſubvert the Eſtabliſh'd Religion and Government; I ſhall inſert <hi>verbatim</hi> the Declaration of his preſent Majeſty, then Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> which gives a true and lively Scheme of the Condition of the People of <hi>England,</hi> under King <hi>James</hi> his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and grounds the Lawfulneſs and Juſtice of his Arms, who had ſo near a concern in the Succeſſion, upon the Obligation he was under for his Princeſs's, his Own, and the Nation's Intereſt, to interpoſe in order to their deliverance.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>God's Ways of Diſpoſing of Kingdoms.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Declaration of his Highneſs, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Henry,</hi> by the Grace of God, <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> &amp;c. of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons inducing him to appear in Arms in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> for preſerving of the Proteſtant Religion, and for reſtoring the Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. IT is both certain and evident to all men, That the Publick Peace and Happineſs of any State or Kingdom, cannot be preſerved,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41262:6"/>where the Laws, Liberties, and Cuſtoms, eſtabliſhed <hi>by the lawful Authority in it,</hi> are openly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed and annulled: More eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally where the Alteration of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is endeavoured, and that a <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> which is contrary to Law, is endeavoured to be introduced: Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which thoſe who are moſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately concerned in it, are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſably bound to endeavour to preſerve and maintain the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Laws, Liberties, and Cuſtoms, and above all, the <hi>Religion</hi> and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God that is eſtabliſhed among them; and to take ſuch an effectual care, that the Inhabitants of the ſaid State or Kingdom, may neither be deprived of their <hi>Religion,</hi> nor of their Civil Rights: which is ſo much the more neceſſary, becauſe the Greatneſs and Security both of Kings, Royal Families, and of all ſuch as are in Authority, as well as the Happineſs of their Subjects and People, depend in a moſt eſpecial manner, upon the exact Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Maintenance of theſe their Laws, Liberties, and Cuſtoms.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Upon theſe grounds it is, that we cannot any longer forbear to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That to our great Regret, we ſee that thoſe Counſellors, who have now the chief Credit with the King, have overturned the <hi>Religion,</hi> Laws and Liberties of thoſe Realms, and ſubjected them in all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to their Conſciences, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Properties, to Arbitrary Government, and that not only by ſecret and indirect ways, but in an open and undiſguiſed manner.</p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41262:6"/>
                     <p n="3">3. Thoſe Evil Counſellors, for the advancing and colouring this with ſome plauſible pretexts, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and ſet on foot the King's <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing Power;</hi> by Virtue of which they pretend, that according to <hi>Law,</hi> he can <hi>ſuſpend</hi> and <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with the Execution of the <hi>Laws</hi> that have been enacted by the <hi>Authority of the King and Parliament,</hi> for the Security and Happineſs of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ſo have rendred thoſe laws of no effect; tho there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certain, than that <hi>as no Laws can be made, but by the joynt concurrence of King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſo</hi> likewiſe <hi>Laws ſo enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> which ſecure the Publick Peace, and Safety of the nation, and the Lives and Liberties of every Subject in it, <hi>cannot be Repealed or Suſpended, but by the ſame Authority.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. for tho the King may pardon the Puniſhment that a Tranſgreſſor has incurred, and to which he is condemned, as in the Caſes of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> or <hi>Felony;</hi> yet it cannot be with any colour of Reaſon inferred from thence, That the King can entirely ſuſpend the Execution of thoſe Laws relating to <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Felony;</hi> unleſs it is pretended, that he is clothed with a Deſpotick and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power; and that the Lives, Liberties, Honours, and Eſtates of the Subjects, depend wholly on his good Will and Pleaſure, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſubject to him; which muſt infallibly follow, on the King's ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a power to ſuſpend the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and to diſpence with them.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41262:7"/>
                     <p n="5">5. thoſe Evil Counſellors, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the giving ſome Credit to <hi>this ſtrange and execrable Maxim,</hi> have ſo conducted the Matter, that they have obtained a Sentence from the Judges, declaring, That this <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> is a Right belonging to the <hi>Crown;</hi> as if it were in the power of the Twelve Judges to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up the Laws, Rights, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the whole Nation, to the King, to be diſpoſed of by him Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily and at his Pleaſure, and expreſly contrary to Laws enacted for the Security of the Subjects. In order to the obtaining this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe Evil Counſellors did before-hand examine ſecretly the Opinion of the Judges, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch of them as could not in Conſcience concur in ſo pernicious a Sentence, to be turned out, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be ſubſtituted in their rooms, till by the Changes which were made in the Courts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, they at laſt obtained that Judgment. And they have raiſed ſome to thoſe Truſts, who make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſſion of the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tho thoſe are by Law rendred incapable of all ſuch Employments.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. It is alſo manifeſt and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, That as his Majeſty was upon his coming to the Crown, received and acknowledged by all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as their <hi>King,</hi> without the leaſt Oppoſition, tho he made then open Profeſſion of the <hi>Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> ſo he did then promiſe, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſwear at his Coronation, That he would maintain his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41262:7"/>in the free Enjoyment of their Laws and Liberties; and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, That he would maintain the <hi>Church of England as it was Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law:</hi> It is likewiſe certain, That there have been at divers and ſundry times, ſeveral Laws enacted for the Preſervation of thoſe enacted for the Preſervation of thoſe Rights and Liberties, and of the Proteſtant Religion; and among other Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, it has been enacted, That all Perſons whatſoever, that are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to any Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, or to bear Office in either Univerſity, as likewiſe all other that ſhould be put in any Employment, Civil or Military, ſhould declare that they were not Papiſts, but were of the Proteſtant Religion, and that by their taking of the Oaths of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> yet theſe Evil Counſellors have in effect annulled and aboliſhed all thoſe Laws, both with relation to Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and Civil Employments.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. In order to Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Offices, they have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without any colour of Law, but againſt moſt expreſs Laws to the contrary, ſet up a Commiſſion of a certain number of perſons, to whom they have committed the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance and Direction of all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical matters; in the which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion there has been, and ſtill is one of his Majeſties Miniſters of State, who makes now publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Popiſh Religion, and who at the time of his firſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, declared, That for a great while before, he had believed that to be the only true Religion. By all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41262:8"/>this, the deplorable State to which the Proteſtant Religion is reduced, is apparent, ſince the Affairs of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are now put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of perſons who have accepted of a Commiſſion that is manifeſtly illegal, and who have executed it contrary to all Law; and that now one of their chief Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers has abjured the <hi>Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and declared himſelf a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> by which he is become uncapable of holding any publick Employment. The ſaid Commiſſioners have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to given ſuch proof of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Directions given them, that there is no reaſon to doubt, but they will ſtill continue to promote all ſuch deſigns as will be moſt agreeable to them. And thoſe Evil Counſellors take care to raiſe none to any Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, but perſons that have no Zeal for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and that now hide their unconcernedneſs for it, under the ſpecious pretence of <hi>Moderation.</hi> The ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have ſuſpended the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> only becauſe he refuſed to obey an Order that was ſent him, to ſuſpend a worthy Divine, without ſo much as citing him before him to make his own Defence, or obſerving the common forms of Proceſs. They have turned out a Preſident choſen by the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen-College,</hi> and afterwards all the Fellows of that College, without ſo much as citing them before any Court that could take legal Cognizance of that Affair, or obtaining any Sentence againſt them by a competent Judge.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41262:8"/>And the only reaſon that was given for turning them out, was their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to chuſe for their Preſident, a perſon that was recommended to them, by the Inſtigation of thoſe Evil Counſellors, tho the Right of a Free Election belong'd undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them. But they were turned out of their Free-holds contrary to Law, and to that expreſs proviſion in the <hi>Magna Charta, That no man ſhall loſe Life or Goods, but by the Law of the Land.</hi> And now theſe Evil Counſellors have put the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege wholly into the hands of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; tho, as is aboveſaid, they are incapable of all ſuch Employments, both by the Law of the Land, and the Statutes of the College. Theſe Commiſſioners have alſo cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them all the Chancellors and Archdeacons of <hi>England,</hi> requiring them to certifie to them the Names of all ſuch Clergy-men as have read the King's Declaration for <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience,</hi> and of ſuch as have not read it, without conſidering that the reading of it was not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the Clergy by the Biſhops who are their Ordinaries. The Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality and Incompetency of the ſaid Court of the Eccleſiaſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners was ſo notoriouſly known, and it did ſo evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that it tended to the Subverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that the moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and Metropolitan of all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſeeing that it was raiſed for no other end, but to oppreſs ſuch perſons as were of eminent Virtue,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41262:9"/>Learning and Piety, refuſed to ſit, or to concur in it.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. And tho there are many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Laws againſt all Churches or Chappels for the exerciſe of the Popiſh Religion, and alſo againſt all Monaſteries and Convents, and more particularly againſt the Order of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> yet thoſe Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors have procured orders for the building of ſeveral Churches and Chappels for the excrciſe of that Religion. They have alſo procured divers Monaſteries to be erected, and in contempt of the Law, they have not only ſet up ſeveral Colleges of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in divers places, for the corrupting of the Youth, but have raiſed up one of the <hi>Order</hi> to be a Privy-Counſellor, and a Miniſter of State. By all which they do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhew, That they are reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by no rules of Law whatſoever, but that they have ſubjected the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Eſtates of the Subjects, and the Eſtabliſh'd Religion, to a Deſpotick Power, and to Arbitrary Government. In all which they are ſerved and ſeconded by thoſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Commiſſioners.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. They have alſo followed the ſame Methods with relation to Civil Affairs; for they have procured or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to examine all Lords Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Deputy-Lieutenants, Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, and all others that were in any publick Employment, if they would concur with the King in the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and all ſuch whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences did not ſuffer them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with their deſigns, were turned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41262:9"/>out, and others were put in their places, who, they believed, would be more compliant to them in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of defeating the Intent and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of thoſe Laws which had been made with ſo much care and caution for the ſecurity of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</hi> And in many of theſe places they have put profeſs'd Papiſts, tho the Law has diſabled them, and warranted the Subjects not to have any regard to their Orders.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. They have alſo invaded the Privileges, and ſeized on the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of moſt of thoſe Towns that have a right to be repreſented by their Burgeſſes in Parliament, and have procured Surrenders to be made of them, by which the Magiſtrates in them have delivered up all their Rights and Privileges, to be diſpoſed of at the pleaſure of thoſe Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, who have thereupon placed new Magiſtrates in thoſe Towns, ſuch as they can moſt entirely confide in; and in many of them they have put Popiſh Magiſtrates, notwithſtanding the Incapacities under which the Law hath put them.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. And whereas no Nation whatſoever can ſubſiſt without the adminiſtration of good and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Juſtice, upon which mens Lives, Liberties, Honours and Eſtates do depend, thoſe Evils Counſellors have ſubjected theſe to an Arbitrary and Deſpotick Power: In the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Affairs they have ſtudied to diſcover before-hand the Opinions of the Judges, and have turned out ſuch as they found would not conform themſelves to their Intentions, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41262:10"/>have put others in their places, of whom they were more aſſured, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any regard to their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. And they have not ſtuck to raiſe even profeſſed Papiſts to the Courts of Judicature, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Incapacity by Law; and that no regard is due to any Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces flowing from them. They have carried this ſo far, as to deprive ſuch Judges, who in the common admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Juſtice, ſhewed that they were governed by their Conſciences, and not by the Directions which the others gave them. By which it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that they deſign to render themſelves the abſolute Maſters of the Lives, Honours and Eſtates of the Subjects, of what rank or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſoever they may be; and that without having any regard either to the Equity of the Cauſe, or to the Conſciences of the Judges, whom they will have to ſubmit in all things to their own Will and Pleaſure; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping by ſuch ways to intimidate thoſe who are yet in Employment, as alſo ſuch others, as they ſhall think fit, to put in the rooms of thoſe whom they have turned out; and to make them ſee what they muſt look for, if they ſhould at any time act in the leaſt contrary to their good-liking, and that no failings of that kind are pardoned in any Perſons whatſoever. A great deal of Blood has been ſhed in many places of the Kingdom, by Judges governed by thoſe Evil Counſellors, againſt all the Rules and Forms of Law, without ſo much as ſuffering the Perſons that were accuſed to plead in their own Defence.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41262:10"/>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">12. They have alſo, by putting the Adminiſtration of Juſtice in the hands of Papiſts, brought all the Matters of Civil Juſtice into great uncertainties; with how much Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs and Juſtice ſoever that theſe Sentences may have been given. For ſince the Laws of the Land do not only exclude Papiſts from all Places of Judicature, but have put them under an Incapacity; none are bound to acknowledge, or to obey their Judgments, and all Sentences given by them are null and void of themſelves: So that all Perſons who have been caſt in Tryals before ſuch Popiſh Judges, may juſtly look on their pretended Sentences as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no more force than the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of any private and unauthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Perſon whatſoever. So deplorable is the Caſe of the Subjects, who are obliged to anſwer to ſuch Judges, that muſt in all things ſtick to the Rules which are ſet them by thoſe Evil Counſellors, who as they raiſe them up to thoſe Employments, ſo can turn them out of them at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and who can never be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lawful Judges; ſo that all their Sentences are in the Conſtruction of the Law, of no Force and Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy. They have likewiſe diſpoſed of all Military Employments, in the ſame manner: For tho the Laws have not only excluded Papiſts from all ſuch Employments, but have in particular provided, that they ſhould be diſarmed; yet they, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of theſe Laws, have not only armed the Papiſts, but have likewiſe raiſed them up to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41262:11"/>Military Truſt, both by Sea and Land, and that Strangers as well as Natives, and <hi>Iriſh</hi> as well as <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that ſo by thoſe means, having ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred themſelves Maſters both of the Affairs of the Church, of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation, and of the Courts of Juſtice, and ſubjected them all to a Deſpotick and Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Power, they might be in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to maintain and execute their wicked Deſigns, by the aſſiſtance of the Army, and thereby to enſlave the Nation.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. The diſmal effects of this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Eſtabliſhed Religion, Laws and Liberties in <hi>England,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more evidently to us, by what we ſee done in <hi>Ireland;</hi> where the whole Government is put in the Hands of Papiſts, where all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Inhabitants are under the daily fears of what may be juſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended from the Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which is ſet up there: which has made great numbers of them leave that Kingdom, and abandon their Eſtates in it, remembring well that Cruel and Bloody Maſſacre which fell out in that Iſland in the Year 1641.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Thoſe Evil Counſellors have alſo prevailed with the King to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in <hi>Scotland,</hi> That he is cloathed with <hi>Abſolute Power,</hi> and that all the Subjects are bound <hi>to obey him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſerve:</hi> upon which he has aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an Arbitrary Power both over the Religion and Laws of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; from all which it is apparent, what is to be looked for in <hi>England,</hi> as ſoon as matters are duly prepared for it.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41262:11"/>
                     <p n="15">15. Thoſe great and inſufferable Oppreſſions, and the open Contempt of all Law, together with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the ſad Conſequences that muſt certainly follow upon it, have put the Subjects under great and juſt Fears; and have made them look after ſuch lawful Remedies as are allowed of in all Nations: yet all has been without effect. And thoſe Evil Counſellors have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make all Men apprehend the loſs of their Lives, Liberties, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Eſtates, if they ſhould go about to preſerve themſelves from this Oppreſſion, by Petition, Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, or other means authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Law. Thus did they proceed with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the other Biſhops, who having offered a moſt humble Petition to the King, in terms full of Reſpect, and not exceeding the number limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Law, in which they ſet forth in ſhort, the Reaſons for which they could not obey that Order, which, by the Inſtigation of thoſe Evil Counſellors, was ſent them, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to appoint their Clergy to read in their Churches the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> were ſent to priſon, and afterwards brought to a Tryal, as if they had been guilty of ſome enormous Crime. They were not only obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves in that purſuit, but to appear before profeſſed Papiſts, who had not taken the Teſt, and by conſequence were Men whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt led them to condemn them; and the Judges that gave their Opinion in their favours, were thereupon turned out.</p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41262:12"/>
                     <p n="16">16. And yet it cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that any Kings, how great ſoever their Power has been, and how Arbitrary and Deſpotick ſoever they have been in the exerciſe of it, have ever reckoned it a Crime for their Subjects to come in all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Reſpect, and in a due number, not exceeding the limits of the Law, and repreſent to them the Reaſons that made it impoſſible for them to obey their Orders. Thoſe Evil Counſellors have alſo treated a Peer of the Realm as a Criminal, only becauſe he ſaid, That the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects were not bound to obey the Orders of a Popiſh Juſtice of Peace; though it is evident, that they being by Law rendred incapable of all ſuch Truſts, no regard is due to their Order. This being the ſecurity which the People have by the Law for their Lives, Liberties, Honours and Eſtates, That they are not to be ſubjected to the Arbitrary Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Papiſts, that are contrary to Law, put into any Employment Civil or Military.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Both We our ſelves, and our Deareſt and moſt Entirely Beloved Conſort the Princeſs, have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſignify, in terms full of reſpect to the King, the juſt and deep Regret which all theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings have given us; and in Compliance with his Majeſty's De\ſires ſignified to us, We declared both by Word of Mouth, to his Envoy, and in Writing, what our Thoughts were touching the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing of the <hi>Teſt and Penal Laws;</hi> which we did in ſuch a manner, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41262:12"/>we hoped we had propoſed an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient by which the Peace of thoſe Kingdoms, and a happy Agreement among the Subjects of all Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, might have been ſetled: but thoſe Evil Counſellors have put ſuch ill Conſtructions on theſe our good Intentions, that they have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to alienate the King more and more from us; as if We had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to diſturb the Quiet and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. The laſt and great Remedy for all thoſe Evils, is <hi>the calling of a Parliament,</hi> for ſecuring the Nation againſt the evil Practices of thoſe wicked Counſellors: But this could not be yet compaſſed, nor can it be eaſily brought about. For thoſe Men apprehending, that a Lawful Parliament being once aſſembled, they would be brought to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for all their open Violations of Law, and for their Plots and Conſpiracies againſt the Proteſtant Religion, and the Lives, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject, they have endeavoured, under the ſpecious Pretence of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> firſt to ſow Diviſions among Proteſtants, between thoſe of the <hi>Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenters:</hi> The deſign being laid to engage Proteſtants, that are ail equally concerned, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves from Popiſh Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, into mutual Quarrellings, that ſo by theſe, ſome Advantages might be given to them to bring about their Deſigns; and that both in the Election of the Members of Parliament, and afterwards in the Parliament it ſelf. For they ſee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41262:13"/>well, that if all Proteſtants could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a mutual good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with another, and concur together in the preſerving of their Religion, it would not be poſſible for them to compaſs their wicked Ends. They have alſo required all Perſons in the ſeveral Counties of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> that either were in any Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, or were in any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eſteem, to declare before-hand that they would concur in the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt and Penal Laws;</hi> and that they would give their Voices in the Elections to Parliament, only for ſuch as would concur in it; ſuch as would not thus preingage themſelves, were turned out of all Employments; And others who entred into thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, were put into their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, many of them being Papiſts: And contrary to the Charters and Privileges of thoſe Burroughs that have a Right to ſend Burgeſſes to Parliament, they have ordered ſuch Regulations to be made, as they thought fit and neceſſary, for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves of all the Members that are to be choſen by thoſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations: and by this means they hope to avoid that Puniſhment which they have deſerved; tho it is apparent, that all Acts made by Popiſh Magiſtrates are null and void of themſelves: So that no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament can be Lawful, for which the Elections and Returns are made by Popiſh Sheriffs and Mayors of Towns; and therefore as long as the Authority and Magiſtracy is in ſuch hands, it is not poſſible to have any Lawful Parliament. And tho ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41262:13"/>to the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and Immemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Cuſtom, all Elections of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-men ought to be made with an entire Liberty, without any ſort of Force, or the requiring the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to chuſe ſuch Perſons as ſhall be named to them; and the Perſons thus freely elected, ought to give their Opinions freely, upon all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are brought before them, having the good of the Nation ever before their eyes, and following in all things the Dictates of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; yet now the People of <hi>England</hi> cannot expect a Remedy from a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> legally called and choſen. But they may perhaps ſee one called, in which all Elections will be carried by Fraud or Force, and which will be compoſed of ſuch Perſons, of whom thoſe Evil Counſellors hold themſelves well aſſured, in which all things will be carried on according to their Direction and Intereſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to the Good or Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Nation; which may appear evidently from this, that the ſame Perſons tried the Members of the laſt Parliament, to gain them to Conſent to the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt and Penal Laws,</hi> and procured that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be diſſolved, when they found that they could not, neither by Promiſes nor Threatnings, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the Members to comply with their wicked Deſigns.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. But to Crown all, there are great and violent Preſumptions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing us to believe, that thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Counſellors, in order to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of their ill Deſigns, and to the gaining to themſelves the more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41262:14"/>time for the effecting of them, for the encouraging of their Complices, and for the diſcouraging of all good Subjects, have publiſhed, That the <hi>Queen</hi> hath brought forth a <hi>Son;</hi> though there have appeared both during the <hi>Queen</hi>'s pretended big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in the manner in which the Birth was managed, ſo many juſt and viſible grounds of Suſpicion, that not only we our ſelves, but all the good Subjects of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, do vehemently ſuſpect, that the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was not born by the <hi>Queen.</hi> And it is notoriouſly known to all the World, that many both doubted of the <hi>Queen</hi>'s Bigneſs, and of the birth of the Child, and yet there was not any one thing done to ſatisfie them, or to put an end to their Doubts.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. And ſince our Deareſt and moſt Entirely beloved Conſort the Princeſs, and likewiſe We Our Selves, have ſo great an Intereſt in this Matter, and ſuch a Right, as all the World knows, to the Succeſſion to the Crown: Since alſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did in the Year 1672. when the States General of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> were invaded in a moſt unjuſt War, uſe their utmoſt endeavours to put an end to that War, and that in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to thoſe who were then in the Government; and by their ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they ran the hazard of loſing both the Favour of the Court, and their employments: and ſince the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation has ever teſtified a moſt particular Affection and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, both to our Deareſt Conſort the Princeſs, and to Our ſelves,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41262:14"/>We cannot excuſe our ſelves from Eſpouſing their Intereſts, in a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch high Conſequence; and from contributing all that lies in us, for the maintaining both of the <hi>proteſtant Religion,</hi> and of the Laws and Liberties of thoſe Kingdoms, and for the Securing to them the continual enjoyment of all their juſt Rights. To the doing of which, We are moſt earneſtly ſolicited by a great many Lords, both Spiritual and Temporal, and by many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and other Subjects of all Ranks.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Therefore it is, that We have thought fit to go over to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and to carry over with us a Force, ſufficient by the Bleſſing of God, to defend us from the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thoſe Evil Counſellors. And We being deſirous that our Intentions in this may be rightly underſtood, have for this end pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared this <hi>Declaration,</hi> in which, as we have hitherto given a True Account of the Reaſons inducing us to it; ſo we now think fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That this our Expedition is intended for no other deſign, but to have a Free and Lawful Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Aſſembled, as ſoon as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: And that in order to this, all the late Charters by which the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Burgeſſes are limited con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Ancient Cuſtom, ſhall be conſidered as null and of no force: And likewiſe all Magiſtrates who have been unjuſtly turned out, ſhall forthwith reſurne their former employments, as well as all the Burroughs of <hi>England</hi> ſhall return again to their Ancient preſcriptions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41262:15"/>and Charters; and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, that the Ancient Charter of the Great and Famous City of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall again be in force: And that the Writs for the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of parliament ſhall be addreſſed to the proper Officers, according to Law and Cuſtome. That alſo none be ſuffered to chuſe, or to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Members of Parliament, but ſuch as are qualified by Law: And that the Members of Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus lawfully Choſen, they ſhall meet and ſit in full Freedom; that ſo the two Houſes may concur in the preparing of ſuch Laws, as they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on full and free Debate ſhall judge neceſſary and convenient, both for the confirming and executing the Law concerning the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and ſuch other Laws as are neceſſary for the ſecurity and maintenance of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion;</hi> as likewiſe for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch Laws as may eſtabliſh a good agreement between the <hi>Church of England</hi> and all <hi>Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> as alſo for the covering and ſecuring of all ſuch who will live peaceably under the Government, as becomes good Subject, from all perſecution upon the account of their Religion, even <hi>Papiſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not excepted; and for the doing of all other things, which the Two Houſes of Parliament ſhall find neceſſary for the Peace, Honour and Safety of the Nation, ſo that there may be no more danger of the Nations falling at any time hereafter under <hi>Arbitrary Government.</hi> To this Parliament we will alſo refer the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the Birth of the pretended
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41262:15"/>Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and of all things relating to it, and to the Right of Succeſſion.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. And We, for our part, will concur in every thing that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Peace and Happineſs of the Nation, which a Free and Lawful Parliament ſhall determine; ſince we have nothing before our Eyes in this our undertaking, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the Covering of all men from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for their Conſciences, and the ſecuring to the whole Nation the free enjoyment of all their Laws, Rights and Liberties, under a Juſt and Legal Government.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. This is the Deſign that we have propoſed to our ſelves, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing upon this occaſion in Arms: In the Conduct of which, We will keep the Forces under our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, under all the ſtrictneſs of Martial Diſcipline; and take a ſpecial care, that the people of the Countries through which we muſt March, ſhall not ſuffer by their means; and as ſoon as the ſtate of the Nation will admit of it, We promiſe that we will ſend back all thoſe Foreign Forces that We have brought along with us.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. We do therefore hope that all people will judge rightly of us, and approve of theſe our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: But We chiefly rely on the Bleſſing of God for the Succeſs of this our Undertaking, in which We place our whole and only Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. We do in the laſt place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite and require all perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41262:16"/>all the Peers of the Realm both Spiritual and Temporal, all Lords Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and all Gentlemen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and other Commons of all ranks, to come and aſſiſt us, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Executing of this our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, againſt all ſuch as ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Oppoſe us; that ſo we may prevent all thoſe Miſeries which muſt needs follow upon the Nations being kept under Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Slavery: And that the Violences and Diſorders which have overturned the whole Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, may be fully redreſſed in a <hi>Free and Legal Parliament.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="26">26. And we do likewiſe reſolve, that as ſoon as the Nations are brought to a ſtate of Quiet, We will take care that a Parliament ſhall be called in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the reſtoring the Ancient Conſtitution of that Kingdom, and for bringing the Matters of Religion to ſuch a Settlement, that the people may live eaſie and happy, and for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an end to all the unjuſt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, that have been in a courſe of ſo many years committed there.</p>
                     <p>We will alſo ſtudy to bring the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſuch a ſtate, that the Settlement there may be religiouſly obſerved; and that the Proteſtant and Britiſh Intereſt there, may be ſecured. And we will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all poſſible means, to procure ſuch an Eſtabliſhment in all the Three Kingdoms, that they may all live in a happy Union and Correſpondence together; and that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41262:16"/>the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace, Honour and Happineſs of thoſe Nations, may be eſtabliſhed upon laſting Foundations.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given under our Hand and Seal, at our Court in the</hi> Hague, <date>
                              <hi>the Tenth day of</hi> October, <hi>in the year of our Lord,</hi> 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>William Henry,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>By his Highneſs ſpecial Command,</hi> C. Huygens,</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The King having received advice that the preparations in <hi>Holland</hi> were deſigned for <hi>England,</hi> caſt about how to prevent the Peoples running to joyn with the Prince: In order to which he was adviſed to appeaſe them, by ſeeming to ſtep backward, and undo ſome things that he knew had given a general diſtaſte againſt his Government. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion was taken away, the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and the Maſter and Fellows of <hi>Magdalen-College</hi> reſtored; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Ancient Charters of Cities and Boroughs, and a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment promiſed to be called, when the Kingdom ſhould be freed from a Foreign Force.</p>
               <p>This occaſioned the Prince to publiſh his Additional Declaration.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>His Highneſs's additional Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AFter we had Prepared and Printed this our Declartion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41262:17"/>We have underſtood that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters of the Religion and Laws of thoſe Kingdoms, hearing of Our Preparations to aſſiſt the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, have begun to retract ſome of the Arbitrary and Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Powers that they had aſſumed, and to vacate ſome of their Injuſt Judgments and Decrees. The ſenſe of their Guilt, and the diſtruſt of their Force, have induced them to offer to the City of <hi>London</hi> ſome ſeeming Relief from their great Oppreſſions; hoping thereby to quiet the People, and to divert them from demanding a Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of their Religion and Laws under the ſhelter of our Arms: They do alſo give out, That we do intend to Conquer and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave the Nation; and therefore it is that we have thought fit to add a few words to our Declaration.</p>
                     <p>We are confident, that no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can have ſuch hard thoughts of us, As to imagine that we have any other Deſign in this Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, than to procure a Settlement of the Religion, and of the Liberties and Properties of the Subjects upon ſo ſure a Foundation, that there may be no danger of the Nations relapſing into the like Miſeries at any time hereafter. And as the Forces that we have brought along with us, are utterly diſproportioned to that wicked Deſign of Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Nation, if we were capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Intending it; ſo the great numbers of the Principal Nobility and Gentry, that are Men of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Quality and Eſtates, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41262:17"/>of known Integrity and Zeal both for the Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> many of them being alſo diſtinguiſhed by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Fidelity to the Crown, who do both accompany us in this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and have earneſtly ſolicited us to it, will cover us from all ſuch malicious Inſinuations: For it is not to be imagin'd, that either thoſe who have Invited us, or thoſe that are already come to Aſſiſt us, can join in a wicked attempt of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, to make void their own law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Titles to their Honours, Eſtates, and Intereſts. We are alſo confident, that all Men ſee how little weight there is to be laid on all Promiſes and Engagements, that can be now made; ſince there has been ſo little regard had in the time paſt, to the moſt ſolemn Promiſes. And as that imperfect Redreſs that is now offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is a plain Confeſſion of thoſe Violations of the Government that we have ſet forth; ſo the Defective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it is no leſs apparent: For they lay down nothing which they may not take up at pleaſure; and they reſerve entire, and not ſo much as mentioned, their Claims and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to an Arbitrary and Deſpotick Power; which has been the Root of all their Oppreſſion, and of the total Subverſion of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And it is plain, that there can be no Redreſs nor Remedy offered but in Parliament; by a Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Rights of the Subjects, that have been invaded, and not by any pretended Acts of Grace, to which the extremity of their Affairs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41262:18"/>has driven them. Therefore it is that we have thought fit to declare, That we will refer all to a Free Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the Nation, in a Lawful Parliament.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given under our Hand and Seal, at our Court in the</hi> Hague, <date>
                              <hi>the Twenty fourth day of</hi> October, <hi>in the year of our Lord,</hi> 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>William Henry, <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange.</signed>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>By his Highneſs's ſpecial Command,</hi> C. Huygens.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Purſuant to the Peoples Invitation, and to carry on the ends oſ the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Declaration, the Prince ſet Sail from <hi>Holland,</hi> with betwixt Four and Five Hundred Capital Ships, Fire-Ships, Pinks, and Tenders: And upon the Fifth of <hi>November</hi> landed in <hi>Torbay</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The people in great Numbers welcom'd his Highneſs with loud Acclamations of Joy. His Army conſiſted of about 15000 Horſe and Foot.</p>
               <p>After the Army was landed, and the Prince come to <hi>Exeter,</hi> the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from all parts of <hi>Devonſhire, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſetſhire,</hi> &amp;c. flock'd to him in great numbers, few abſenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Several of the Nobility came to him likewiſe, whilſt in and about <hi>Exeter;</hi> others afterwards, when he was farther advanced towards <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before his Roayl Highneſs left <hi>Exeter,</hi> there was an Aſſociation drawn up, and ſigned by all the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41262:18"/>Lords and Gentlemen that were with him, in theſe words; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WE whoſe Names are hereunto ſubſcribed, who have now joyned with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> for the defence of the Proteſtant Religion, and for the maintaining the Ancient Government, and the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> do engage to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſtick firm to this Cauſe, and to one another, in the defence of it, and never to depart from it, until our Religion, Laws, and Liberties are ſo far ſecured to us in a Free Parliament, that we ſhall be no more in danger of falling under <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi> And whereas we are engaged in this common Cauſe, under the Protection of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by which in caſe his Perſon may be expoſed to danger, and to the curſed attempts of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and other bloody men; we do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſolemnly engage to God and one another, That if any ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt be made upon him, we will purſue not only thoſe who make it, but all their Adherents, and all that we find in Arms againſt us, with the utmoſt ſeverity of a juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, to their Ruin and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that the execution of any ſuch Attempt (which God of his Infinite Mercy forbid) ſhall not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us from proſecuting this Cauſe which we do now undertake, but that it ſhall engage us to carry it on with all the rigor that ſo barbarous a Practice ſhall deſerve.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41262:19"/>
               <p>About this time a Printed Letter was diſperſed amongſt the Army, directed to the Officers, and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to join with the Prince in the Deliverance of their Countrey.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen and Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE have given you ſo full and ſo true an Account of our Intentions in this Expedition, in our <hi>Declaration,</hi> that as we can add no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it, ſo we are ſure you can deſire nothing more of us. We are come to preſerve your Religion, and to reſtore and eſtabliſh your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties; and therefore we cannot ſuffer our ſelves to doubt, but that all true Engliſh-men will come and concur with us in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſecure theſe Nations from <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi> You muſt all plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that you are only made uſe of as Inſtruments to enſlave the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ruin the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and when that is done, you may judge what you your ſelves ought to expect, both from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiering all the Proteſtant and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Officers and Soldiers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Soldiers being brought over to be put in your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and of which you have ſeen <hi>ſo freſh an Inſtance,</hi> that we need not put you in mind of it. You know how many of your Fellow-Officers have been uſed, for their ſtanding firm to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> and you cannot flatter your ſelves ſo far, as to expect to be better uſed, if thoſe who have broke their Word ſo often ſhould by your means be brought
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41262:19"/>out of thoſe ſtraights to which they are at preſent reduced. We hope likewiſe, that ye will not ſuffer your ſelves to be abuſed by a falſe Notion of Honour, but that you will in the firſt place conſider, what you owe to Almighty God and your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to your Countrey, to your Selves, and to your Poſterity, which you, as Men of Honour, ought to prefer to all private Conſiderations and Engagements whatſoever. We do therefore expect that you will conſider the Honour that is now ſet before you, of being the Inſtruments of ſerving your Countrey, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your Religion; and we ſhall ever remember the Service you ſhall do Us upon this occaſion; and will promiſe you, That we ſhall place ſuch particular Marks of our Favour on every one of you, as your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour at this time ſhall deſerve of Us and the Nation; in which we ſhall make a great diſtinction of thoſe that ſhall come ſeaſonably to joyn their Arms with Ours; and you ſhall find Us to be your well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhing and aſſured Friend,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. H. P. O.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And another to all the Officers and Seamen in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen and Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AS We have given to our Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Well-beloved Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Herbert</hi> a full power, ſo we hope that you will give him an intire cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, as to all he ſhall ſay to you on our part. We have publiſhed a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41262:20"/>which contains the Reaſons which moved Us to enter upon this Expedition; in which you will ſee We had no other deſign than the preſervation of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the re-eſtabliſhment of the Laws and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the Papiſts have reſolved the intire ruin of Our Religion in Great <hi>Britain,</hi> as it is effected alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>France:</hi> And to you it is only to be imputed, if they are Maſters.</p>
                     <p>We are perſuaded that you alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perceive that you are made uſe of only as an Inſtrument for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves and your Countrey under the yoke of the Papacy, and into Slavery, by the means of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and other Foreigners who are prepared to finiſh your Deſtruction And therefore we hope God will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire you with more ſalutary thoughts for the facilitating your Deliverance, and for the delivering you from all your Miſeries, with your Countrey and Religion.</p>
                     <p>And this is in all appearance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, without your joyning with us, and aſſiſting us, who ſeek nothing but your Deliverance. And we alſo aſſure you, That we wlll never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Services which you ſhall do us on this occaſion; and we promiſe to give every one particular marks of our favour, who ſhall deſerve it of us and the Nation. We are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely your very affectionate Friend,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. H. P. O.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41262:20"/>
               <p>Theſe Letters were ſpread under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand over the whole Kingdom, and read by all ſorts of men; and the reaſon of them being undeniable, it had a great force on the Spirits of the Soldiery and Seamen; ſo that thoſe who did not preſently comply with them, yet reſolved they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtrike one ſtroke in the quarrel, till they had a Parliament to ſecure the Religion, Laws and Liberties of <hi>England;</hi> which the Court on the other ſide had reſolved ſhould not be called till the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with his Army, were expelled out of the Nation, and all thoſe who had ſubmitted to him, were reduced into their power, to be treated as they thought fit.</p>
               <p>The particulars of the Prince's March to <hi>London,</hi> where he arrived on the 18th. of <hi>December;</hi> and the very few Skirmiſhes that hapned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſome of his and the King's Soldiers, being inconſiderable, ſhall not be recounted.</p>
               <p>But betwixt his Landing, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Town,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Lord <hi>Delamere</hi> aſſembled Fifty Horſemen, and at the head of them marched to <hi>Mancheſter;</hi> and the next day, to <hi>Boden-Downs,</hi> being then a Hundred and fifty ſtrong, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring his deſign to join with the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> which he did.</item>
                     <item>2. On the <hi>22d</hi> day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> made this Declaration.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41262:21"/>
               <p>WE the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of theſe <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Counties, aſſembled at <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> for the defence of the Laws, Religion and Properties, according to the free-born Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges deſcended to Us from our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, as the undoubted Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of the Subjects of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> (not doubting but the Infringers and Invaders of our Rights, will repreſent us to the reſt of the Nation, in the moſt malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dreſs they can put upon us) do here unanimouſly think it our duty to declare to the reſt of our Proteſtant Fellow-Subjects, the grounds of our preſent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking.</p>
               <p>We are by innumerable Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made ſenſible, That the very Fundamentals of our Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Properties, are about to be rooted out by our late <hi>Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Privy-Council,</hi> as has been of late too apparent: Firſt, By the King's diſpenſing with all the Eſtabliſhed Laws, at his pleaſure. 2. By diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing all Officers out of all Offices of Truſt and Advantage, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing others in their room, that are known Papiſts, deſervedly made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable by the Eſtaſtliſhed Laws of this Land. 3. By deſtroying the Charters of moſt Corporations in the land. 4. By diſcouraging all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are not Papiſts, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring ſuch as turn to Popery. 5. By diſplacing all honeſt and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judges, unleſs they would, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Conſciences, declare
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41262:21"/>that to be Law, which was merely Arbitrary. 6. By branding all Men with the name of Rebels, that but offered to juſtify the Laws in a legal courſe againſt the Arbitrary Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the King, or any of his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Miniſters. 7. By burthening the Nation with an Army, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Violation of the Rights of the Subjects; and by diſcountenancing the Eſtabliſhed Religion. 8. By for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the Subjects the benefit of Petitioning, and conſtruing them Libellers; ſo rendring the Laws a Noſe of Wax, to ſerve their Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Ends. And many more ſuch like, too long here to enumerate.</p>
               <p>We being thus made ſadly ſenſible of the Arbitrary Tyrannical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is by the influence of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical</hi> Councils coming upon us, do unanimouſly declare, That not being willing to deliver our Poſterity over to ſuch a condition of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> as the aforeſaid Oppreſſions do inevitably threaten; we will, to the utmoſt of our power, oppoſe the ſame, by joining with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (whom, we hope, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath ſent to reſcue us from the Oppreſſions aforeſaid) will uſe our utmoſt endeavours for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of our almoſt ruin'd Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Religion; and herein we hope all good Proteſtant Subjects will with their Lives and Fortunes be aſſiſtant to us, and not be bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear'd with the opprobrious terms of Rebels, by which they would fright us to become perfect Slaves to their Tyrannical Inſolences and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations: For we aſſure our ſelves,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41262:22"/>that no rational and unbiaſs'd Perſon will judge it Rebellion to defend our Laws and Religion, which all our Princes have ſworn at their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation; which Oath, how well it hath been obſerved of late, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> may have the conſideration of.</p>
               <p>We own it Rebellion to reſiſt a King that governs by Law; but he was always accounted a <hi>Tyrant</hi> that made his <hi>Will the Law;</hi> and to reſiſt ſuch a one, we juſtly eſteem no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, but a neceſſary Defence: And in this Conſideration we doubt not of all honeſt Mens aſſiſtance; and humbly hope for and implore the Great God's Protection, that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts of his People as pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him beſt; it having been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that People can never be of one mind without his Inſpiration, which hath in all Ages confirmed that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>Vox populi eſt vox Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The preſent reſtoring the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and reverſing the oppreſſing and unjuſt Judgment given on <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen-College</hi> Fellows, is plain, are but to ſtill the People, like Plumbs to Children, by deceiving them for a while: But if they ſhall by this Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem be fooled, till this preſent Storm that threatens the Papiſts be paſt, as ſoon as they ſhall be re-ſetled, the former Oppreſſions will be put on with greater vigour; but we hope, <hi>in vain is the Net ſpread in the ſight of the Birds:</hi> For, firſt, The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts old Rule is, that <hi>Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks</hi> (as they term Proteſtants) tho the Popiſh Religion is the greateſt Hereſie. And, ſecondly,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41262:22"/>Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s ſo ill obſerving her Promiſes to the <hi>Suffolk</hi> Men that help'd her to her Throne. And above all, thirdly, the Pope's diſpenſing with the Breach of Oaths, Treaties or Promiſes at his pleaſure, when it makes for the Service of Holy Church, as they term it. Theſe, we ſay are ſuch convincing Reaſons to hinder us from giving credit to the aforeſaid <hi>Mock-ſhews</hi> of Redreſs, that we think our ſelves bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to reſt on no ſecurity that ſhall not be approved by a freely-elected Parliament; To whom, under GOD, we refer our Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The King having marched his Army as far as <hi>Salisbury</hi> to meet the Prince, publiſhed a Proclamation of Pardon to all ſuch of his Subjects as had taken up Arms, and ſided with the Prince, provided they deſerted the Enemy within 20 days; and promiſing Pardon and protection to ſuch Foreigners as would come into his Service; and freedom of paſſage to others to return into their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Countries. But this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was not at all regarded.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When the King was at <hi>Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the Popiſh Party ſeeing their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs grow every day more deſperate, began to employ all their Politicks to invent ſome Remedy for them, and then firſt formed the Deſign of the King's with-drawing, which they grounded upon this Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Expectation, That within two years, or leſs, the Nation would be in ſuch Confuſion, that he might return, and have his Ends of it.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41262:23"/>
               <p n="5">5. In the mean time the King being unmoveably fixed in a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution not to call a Parliament, part of the Army revolted, and went over to the Prince; and the reſt either diſcouraged by the deſertion of them that went, or by the averſeneſs they found in the body of the People from making any oppoſition to the Prince's Arms, or out of a ſenſe that in fighting againſt him, they ſhould fight againſt their own Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and native Country, appeared ſo lukewarm in the Cauſe, that the King did not think fit to hazard a Battel.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Prince <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Grafton,</hi> the Lord <hi>Churchill,</hi> and many others of the Proteſtant Nobility, left the King, and went over to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> then at <hi>Sherborne;</hi> and on the 25th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the night, Princeſs <hi>Ann,</hi> the King's Second Daughter, withdrew privately from <hi>White-hall</hi> with the Lady <hi>Churchill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The going off of theſe Great Men ſtruck the King with terror, and the Army being before much in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, became thereby ſo full of fear and ſuſpicion, that a falſe Alarm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, whether by deſign or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, the King and the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my left <hi>Salisbury;</hi> the Army retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Reading,</hi> and the King to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dover,</hi> and on <hi>Monday</hi> the 26th of <hi>November,</hi> he returned in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The firſt thing the King did, being at <hi>London,</hi> was to remove Sir <hi>Edward Hales</hi> from being Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and to put
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41262:23"/>Sir <hi>Bevill Skelton,</hi> a Proteſtant, in his room. Sir <hi>Edward</hi> had diſpleaſed the whole City to the utmoſt, by planting ſeveral Mortar-pieces on the Walls towards the City; which tho deſigned only to awe it, had more enraged than afrighted them. So that his Majeſty thought he was not ſafe at <hi>White-hall,</hi> ſo long as Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> was Maſter of the <hi>Tower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. On the 28th His Majeſty orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Privy Council the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor to iſſue Writs for the ſitting of a Parliament at <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> the 15th of <hi>January</hi> following. But it was now too late, and the Nation in ſuch a ferment, that it was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded what the Court ſaid or did.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Scotland</hi> was by this time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in as bad a Condition as <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and ſome of the Nobility and Gentry were ſent up with a Petition for a Free Parliament. The Popiſh Chappels at <hi>Briſtol, York, Gloceſter, Worceſter, Shrewsbury, Stafford, Wolverhampton, Bromingham, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> and St. <hi>Edmundsbury,</hi> were about this time demoliſhed, and where-ever the Lords in Arms came, the Papiſts were diſarmed. And in <hi>Norfolk</hi> the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> their Lord Lieutenant, had a great appearance of the Gentry with him, where he and they declared for a Free Parliament, and the Protection of the Proteſtant Religion. This Meeting was at <hi>Norwich</hi> the firſt of <hi>December,</hi> and after that the ſame Declaration was renewed at <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and <hi>Lyn,</hi> and the <hi>Suffolk</hi>-Men approved of it, but wanted a Lord Lieutenant to aſſemble and head
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41262:24"/>them in order to the ſhewing their concurrence with ſafety.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Briſtol</hi> was ſeized by the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> and Sir <hi>John Guiſe;</hi> the Lord <hi>Lovelace,</hi> who had been ſeized as he was going to join the Prince, was by the Gentry of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſhire</hi> delivered out of the Caſtle of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> where till then he had been impriſoned. The Lords <hi>Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neux</hi> and <hi>Aſhton</hi> in the mean time ſeized <hi>Cheſter</hi> for the King, being <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and <hi>Berwick</hi> ſtood firm to him; but <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Lord <hi>Lumly,</hi> and declared for a Free Parliament, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion. <hi>York</hi> was in the hands of the Aſſociated Lords: and the Gariſon of <hi>Hull</hi> ſeized the Lord <hi>Langdale</hi> their Governour, a Papiſt, and the Lord <hi>Mountgomery,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed ſome Popiſh Forces newly ſent thither; and then declared for a Free Parliament, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. And <hi>Plimouth</hi> had long before ſubmitted to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. The Popiſh Party was grown ſo contemptible, that on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 6th of <hi>December,</hi> there was a Hue and Cry after Father <hi>Peters,</hi> publickly cried and ſold in the Streets of <hi>London.</hi> And about the ſame time came out a Third Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Prince's name, but not emitted by him; which very much alarm'd the Popiſh Party, and as it is thought, contributed very much to the fixing and haſtning the King's Reſolution of leaving the Nation: It was read in many Towns through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi> at the Market-croſs, the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41262:24"/>People univerſally believing, till ſome time after the Princes coming to Town, that it was really pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd by his Order, and no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.</p>
               <p n="13">13. On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 9th of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> Count <hi>Dada,</hi> the Pope's Nuncio, and many others, departed from <hi>VVhite-hall,</hi> and the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Queen, the Child, and (as was ſaid) Father <hi>Peters,</hi> croſſed the Water to <hi>Lambeth</hi> in three Coaches, and with a ſtrong Guard went to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Graves-end,</hi> where they embarked for <hi>France.</hi> It's ſuppoſed ſhe carried the Seal from <hi>VVhite-hall,</hi> and caus'd it to be thrown into the <hi>Thames;</hi> for on the 3d of <hi>May</hi> afterwards it was found in the bottom of the River by a Fiſher-man in a Red-bag, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Lambeth</hi> and <hi>Faux-hall,</hi> and preſented to the King.</p>
               <p>Before this, the Marquiſs of <hi>Halli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Godolphin,</hi> had been ſent by the King and Council to treat with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to adjuſt the Preliminaries in order to the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Parliament, who the Eighth of <hi>December</hi> ſent theſe Propoſals to him.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THE King commanded us to acquaint you, That he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all the differences and cauſes of Complaint alledged by your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſeem to be referred to a <hi>Free Parliament.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Majeſty, as he hath already declared, was reſolved before this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41262:25"/>to call one, but thought that in the preſent ſtate of Affairs, it was adviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to defer it till things were more compoſed; yet ſeeing that his People ſtill continue to deſire it, he hath put forth his Proclamation in order to it, and hath iſſued forth his Writs for the Calling of it.</p>
                     <p>And to prevent any cauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption in it, he will conſent to every thing that can be reaſonably required for the ſecurity of all thoſe that come to it.</p>
                     <p>His Majeſty hath therefore ſent us to attend your Highneſs, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſting of all Matters that ſhall be agreed to be neceſſary to the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Elections, and the Security of Sitting, and is ready to enter immediately into a Treaty in order to it.</p>
                     <p>His Majeſty propoſeth, That in the mean time the reſpective Armies may be retained within ſuch Limits, and at ſuch diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> as may prevent the Apprehenſions that the Parliament may be in any kind diſturbed, being deſirous that the Meeting may be no longer delay'd, than it muſt be by the uſual and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Forms.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Hungerford,</hi> 
                           <date>the 8th of <hi>December,</hi> 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Hallifax,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Nottingham,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Godolphin.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41262:25"/>
               <p>To this his Royal Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> return'd this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE, with the Advice of the Lords and Gentlemen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled with Us, have in Anſwer made theſe following Propoſals.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. That all Papiſts, and ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are not qualified by Law, be Diſarmed, Disbanded, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from all Employments Civil and Military.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. That all Proclamations that reflect upon Us, or any that have come to Us, or declared for Us, be re-called; and that if any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for having aſſiſted Us, have been Committed, that they be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſet at Liberty.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. That for the Security and Safety of the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Cuſtody and Government of the <hi>Tower</hi> be immediately put into the Hands of the ſaid City.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. That if His Majeſty ſhould think fit to be in <hi>London,</hi> during the Sitting of the Parliament, that We may be there alſo, with an equal number of our Guards; and if His Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed to be in any place from <hi>London,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſtance he thinks fit, that We may be the ſame diſtance, and that the reſpective Armies be from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> forty Miles, and that no further Forces be brought into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41262:26"/>
                     <p n="5">V. And that for the Security of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their Trade, <hi>Tilbury</hi> Fort be put into the Hands of the City.</p>
                     <p n="6">VI. That a ſufficient part of the Publick Revenue be aſſigned Us, for the Support and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of our Troops, until the Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Free Parliament.</p>
                     <p n="7">VII. That to prevent the land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>French,</hi> or other Foreign Troops, <hi>Portſmouth</hi> may be put into ſuch Hands, as by His Majeſty and Us ſhall be agreed on.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Littlecot,</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 9. 1688.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Anſwer was ſent to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty on <hi>Monday</hi> the 10th of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> by an Expreſs; which when he received, he gave this Juſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Prince's Propoſals, That they were fairer than he could, or did expect. So that he had no reaſon then to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of his Perſon, but might have continued ſecurely in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and taken care of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and called ſuch a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as both himſelf and the Prince deſired; which might qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and effectually have ſetled this Nation, and prevented all ill Conſequences to his Perſon or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Yet he reſolved to leave the Nation; and ordered all thoſe Writs for the Sitting of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that were not ſent out, to be burnt, and a Caveat to be entred againſt the making uſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41262:26"/>thoſe that were ſent down. And at the ſame time ordered the Earl of <hi>Feverſham</hi> to disband the Army, and diſmiſs the Soldiers.</p>
               <p n="15">15. On <hi>December</hi> the 11th, about Three of the Clock in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the King went down the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in a ſmall Boat towards <hi>Graves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end.</hi> The Principal Officers of the Army thereupon met about Ten of the Clock at <hi>White-hall,</hi> and ſent an Expreſs to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to acquaint him with the Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the King, and to aſſure him, that they would aſſiſt the Lord Mayor, to keep the City quiet till his Highneſs came, and made the Soldiers to enter into his Service.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The ſame day the Lords Spiritual and Temporal about the Town, (the then Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, Ely,</hi> and <hi>Peterborough,</hi> being of the number) came to <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and ſending for the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, made the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Declaration.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in and about the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Aſſembled at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> the 11th of <hi>December. 1688.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE doubt not but the World believes, that in this great and dangerous Conjuncture we are heartily and zealouſly concerned for the Proteſtant Religion, the Laws of the Land, and the Liberties and Properties of the Subject. And we did reaſonably hope, that the King
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41262:27"/>having iſſued out his Proclamation and Writs for a Free Parliament, we might have reſted ſecure under the expectation of that Meeting: But His Majeſty having withdrawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and, as we apprehend, in order to his departure out of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by the pernicious Counſels of perſons ill affected to our Nation and Religion, we cannot, without being wanting to our Duty, be ſilent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe Calamities, wherein the Popiſh Counſels which ſo long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, have miſerably involved theſe Realms. We do therefore u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly reſolve to apply our ſelves to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who with ſo great Kindneſs to theſe Kingdoms, ſo vaſt Expence, and ſo much Hazard, hath underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, by endeavouring to procure a Free Parliament, to reſcue us (with as little effuſion of Chriſtian Blood as poſſible) from the imminent Dangers of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And we do hereby declare, That we will without utmoſt Endeavours aſſiſt his Highneſs, in the obtaining ſuch a Parliament with all ſpeed, wherein our Laws, our Liberties and Properties may be ſecured, the Church of <hi>England</hi> in particular, with a due Liberty to Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and in general, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Beligion and Intereſt, over the whole World, may be ſupported and encouraged, to the Glory of GOD, the Happineſs of the Eſtabliſhed Government in theſe Kingdoms, and the Advantage of all Princes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41262:27"/>and States in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that may be herein concerned.</p>
                     <p>In the mean time we will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preſerve, as much as in us lies, the Peace and Security of theſe great and populous Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the parts adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, by taking care to diſarm all Papiſts, and ſecure all Jeſuits and <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, who are in or about the ſame.</p>
                     <p>And if there be any thing more to be performed by Us, for promoting his Highneſs's Generous Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the publick good, we ſhall be ready to do it, as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Signed—
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>W. Cant.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>T. Ebor.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Pembrook.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Mulgrave.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Thanet.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Craven.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Ailesbury.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Burlington.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Berkeley.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Newport.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Weymouth.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>P. Wincheſter.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>W. Aſaph.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>F. Ely.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Tho. Roffen.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Tho. Petriburg.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>P. Wharton.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>North and Grey.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Chandois.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Montague.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>T. Jermyn.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Vaughan Carbery.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Culpeper.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Crewe.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Oſulſton.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Whereas his Majeſty hath private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Morning withdrawn himſelf, We the Lord Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, whoſe Names are hereunto Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, being aſſembled in <hi>Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:41262:28"/>in <hi>London,</hi> having agreed upon, and Signed a Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in and about the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> the 11th of <hi>December,</hi> 1688. do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Pembrook,</hi> the Right Honourable the Lord Viſcout <hi>Weymouth,</hi> the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Culpeper,</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to attend his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and at the ſame time to acquaint his Highneſs with what we have further done at this Meeting. Dated at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> the 11th of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1688.</p>
               <p>The Lords, before they came down to the City, had appointed the Lord Mayor, Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Common-Council, to be aſſembled, to concert with them the means of preſerving the City and Kingdom; and when the Peers had thus led the way, they preſently reſolved alſo on the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Addreſs to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe Your Highneſs,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE taking into conſideration your Highneſs's fervent Zeal for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to the World in your many hazardous Enterpriſes, wherein it hath pleaſed Almighty God to bleſs you with miraculous Succeſs, do render our deepeſt thanks to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41262:28"/>Majeſty for the ſame, and beg leave to preſent our moſt humble Thanks to your Highneſs, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your appearing in Arms in this Kingdom, to carry on and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect your glorious Deſigns to reſcue <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> from Slavery and Popery, and in a Free Parliament to eſtabliſh the Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of theſe Kingdoms upon a ſure and laſting Foundation.</p>
                     <p>We have hitherto look'd for ſome remedy for thoſe Oppreſſions and imminent Dangers, which we, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Proteſtant Fellow-Subjects, laboured under, from his Majeſties Conceſſions and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences with your Highneſs's juſt and pious purpoſes expreſſed in your Gracious Declaration.</p>
                     <p>But herein finding our ſelves final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſappointed by his Majeſties with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelf, we preſume to make your Highneſs our Refuge; and do in the Name of this Capital City, implore your Highneſs's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and moſt humbly beſeech your Highneſs to repair to this City, where your Highneſs will be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with univerſal Joy and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
                     <p>This Addreſs being approved and Signed, four Aldermen and eight Commoners were appointed to attend his Highneſs with it.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day the Lieutenancy of <hi>London</hi> Signed this following ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41262:29"/>
                        <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and ſent it by Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Knight; Sir <hi>William Ruſſel,</hi> Sir <hi>Baſil Firebrace,</hi> Knights; and <hi>Charles Duncomb,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe Your Highneſs,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE can never ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the deep ſenſe we have conceived, and ſhall ever retain in our Hearts, that your Highneſs has expoſed your Perſon to ſo many Dangers by Sea and Land, for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom, without which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Undertaking, we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably have ſuffered all the Miſeries that <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> could have brought upon us.</p>
                     <p>We have been greatly concerned, that before this time we had not any ſeaſonable opportunity to give your Highneſs and the World a real Teſtimony, That it has been our firm Reſolution, to venture all that is dear to us, to attain thoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ends which your Highneſs has propos'd for reſtoring and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theſe diſtracted Nations.</p>
                     <p>We therefore now unanimouſly preſent to your Highneſs our juſt and due acknowledgments for that happy Relief you have brought to us; and that we may not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this preſent Conjuncture, we have put our ſelves into ſuch a poſture, that (by the bleſſing of God) we may be capable to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all ill Deſigns, and to preſerve this City in Peace and Safety, till your Highneſs's happy Arrival.</p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41262:29"/>
                     <p>We therefore humbly deſire, that your Highneſs will pleaſe to repair to this City with what convenient ſpeed you can, for the perfecting the Great Work which your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has ſo happily begun, to the general joy and ſatisfaction of us all.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. After his Highneſs had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved certain Intelligence that the King was gone back from <hi>Salisbury</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> he came forward by eaſie Journeys, and entred <hi>Salisbury</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 4th of <hi>December.</hi> On the 5th, the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> came thither to him. The ſame day the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Cherbury,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Harley,</hi> and moſt of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>VVorceſterſhire</hi> and <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> met at <hi>VVorceſter,</hi> and declared for the Prince of <hi>Orange. Ludlow</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was alſo taken in for him by the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> and Sir <hi>VValter Blunt,</hi> and the Popiſh Sheriff of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſecured in it by that Peer. The 7th of <hi>December</hi> his Highneſs came on to <hi>Hungerford;</hi> the 8th, the Lords ſent by the King, came thither to him, and had the Diſpatch already mentioned: after Dinner he went to <hi>Lidcot.</hi> The 14th, The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Peers, Common-Council, and Lieutenancy of <hi>London,</hi> preſented three Addreſſes to the Prince at <hi>Henly.</hi> The 15th his Highneſs entred <hi>Windſor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="18">18. The King was ſtopt in his paſſage by ſome who knew him not, but ſeiz'd him and his Company as ſuſpected Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but being at
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41262:30"/>laſt diſcovered, and the noiſe of his being detained at <hi>Feverſham</hi> coming to the Lords at <hi>London,</hi> the Lords <hi>Feverſham, Aylesbury, Yarmouth</hi> and <hi>Middleton</hi> were ſent to entreat his return to <hi>White-hall:</hi> whither he came on the 16th in the Evening. But in the mean time the Rabble at <hi>London</hi> demoliſhed the Popiſh Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and Convent at St. <hi>John</hi>'s, the Convent and Chappel of Fryars in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-Fields,</hi> and the Popiſh Chappels in <hi>Limeſtreet</hi> and <hi>Bucklers-Bury,</hi> and the Chappel at <hi>Wild-houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="19">19. The King being now at <hi>White-hall,</hi> and the Prince at <hi>Windſor,</hi> the King invites the Prince to St. <hi>James</hi>'s; but the Lords at <hi>Windſor</hi> did not think it reaſonable, nor ſafe, either for the King's or the Prince's perſon to be together in one place with their ſeveral Guards. Whereupon the Guards at <hi>White-hall</hi> were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodged by Count <hi>Solmes,</hi> by the Prince's order, and the Prince's Guards placed in their room. And the King was that ſame night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 17th of <hi>December,</hi> deſired by a Meſſage from the Prince to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to ſome place at a reaſonable diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Ham</hi> was propoſed. But the King choſe to return into <hi>Kent,</hi> which he did the next day: and got away privately from the Guards, and embark'd for <hi>France.</hi> The ſame day that the King withdrew from <hi>White-hall</hi> the ſecond time, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, attended by Monſieur <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and a great
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41262:30"/>number of Nobility and Gentry, and was entertain'd with a joy and concourſe of the People, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd free and unconſtrain'd, and all the Bells of the City were rung, and Bonfires in every Street.</p>
                     <p>Thus the body of the People being uneaſie under the Late King's Government, and not thinking it either their Intereſt, or their Duty, to ſupport him in it, who had made uſe of his Authority only to carry on an Intereſt inconſiſtent with the welfare of a Proteſtant Nation, and that by all the Illegal Methods that his Evil Counſellors could adviſe, or durſt put in execution; and who, to awe the People from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any check to his Career, had not only Judges at hand, that would wreſt the Law to ſerve his Ends, without any regard to their Oaths, or the truſt of their Places; but had raiſed an Army in times of Peace, directly againſt Law, and in effect had thereby waged war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Subjects: The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I ſay, being thus affected, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actually join'd with the Prince, or openly declared for him, or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by other demonſtrations their joy for his arrival, and interpoſing betwixt them and utter ruine. Whereupon the King was left to ſhift for himſelf, and flew for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to his old Ally, the Enemy of God and Man.</p>
                     <p>The firſt thing the Prince did when come to Town, after he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41262:31"/>had received the Congratulations of the City by all the Aldermen, and two Common-Council-men for every Ward, and taken care about the Army, was to deſire the Advice of ſuch Lords as were in or about the Town, and of ſuch Gentlemen as had ſerved in any Parliament in the Reign of the Late King <hi>Charles,</hi> what courſe to take for the ſettlement of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Theſe adviſed him to take upon himſelf the Adminiſtration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs, Civil and Military, and the diſpoſal of the Publick Revenue, and to iſſue out Circular Letters for the calling a Convention to meet and fit at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> on the 22d of <hi>January</hi> next enſuing.</p>
                     <p>Which was done accordingly, and the Elections went on with the greateſt liberty that could poſſibly be conceived.</p>
                     <p>The Two Houſes met the 22d of <hi>January,</hi> and the Upper Houſe choſe the Marqueſs of <hi>Halifax</hi> for their Speaker; and the Commons, <hi>Henry Powle,</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> After which a Letter from the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was read to them, Exhorting them to unity, and ſpeed in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations.</p>
                     <p>The Houſes ordered the 31ſt of <hi>January</hi> to be appointed for a day of Publick Thankſgiving to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for delivering this Kingdom from Popery and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power by means of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> That Day to be obſerved in <hi>London</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41262:31"/>
                        <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and ten miles diſtance; and the 14th of <hi>February</hi> after throughout the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p>On the 28th of <hi>January</hi> the Commons paſſed this Vote; <hi>viz. Reſolved, That King</hi> James <hi>the IId having endeavoured to ſubvert the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Kingdom by breaking the Original Contract between King and People; and by the Advice of Jeſuits, and other wicked perſons, having violated the Fundamental Laws, and having with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf out of this Kingdom, hath abdicated the Government, and that the Throne is thereby become Vacant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>On the 6th of <hi>February</hi> the Lords aſſented to the Vote.</p>
                     <p>It will not be material to give a particular Account of the Debates and Conferences that aroſe, and were occaſioned by this and other Votes of the Commons; I haſten to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which was, That on the 12th of <hi>February</hi> the Two Houſes fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed all things in diſpute betwixt them on this manner; <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHereas the late King <hi>James</hi> the Second, by the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of divers Evil Counſellors, Judges and Miniſters employ'd by him, did endeavour to ſubject and extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</p>
                     <p>By aſſuming and exerciſing a power of Diſpenſing with, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41262:32"/>of Laws, and the Execution of Laws, without conſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                     <p>By committing and proſecuting divers worthy Prelates, for hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Petitioning to be excuſed from concurring to the ſaid Aſſumed Power.</p>
                     <p>By iſſuing and cauſing to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted a Commiſſion under the Great Seal, for erecting a Court, call'd <hi>The Court of Commiſſion for Eccleſiaſtical Affairs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By Levying Money for, and to the uſe of the Crown, by pretence of Prerogative, for other time, and in other manner, than the ſame was granted by Parliament.</p>
                     <p>By raiſing and keeping a ſtanding Army within the Kingdom in time of Peace, without conſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and Quartering Soldiers contrary to Law.</p>
                     <p>By cauſing ſeveral good Subjects, being Proteſtants, to be diſarmed, at the ſame time when Papiſts were both Armed and imployed contrary to Law.</p>
                     <p>By violating the Freedom of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Members to ſerve in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                     <p>By Proſecutions in the Court of <hi>King's Bench,</hi> for Matters and Cauſes cognizable only in Parliament, and by divers other Arbitrary and Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Courſes.</p>
                     <p>And whereas of late Years, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, corrupt, and unqualified Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have been returned and ſerved on Juries in Trials, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly divers Jurors in Trials for
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41262:32"/>High-Treaſon, which were not Free-holders.</p>
                     <p>And Exceſſive Bail hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of Perſons committed in Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Caſes, to elude the Benefit of the Laws made for the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
                     <p>And Exceſſive Fines have been impoſed.</p>
                     <p>And Illegal and cruel Puniſhments inflicted.</p>
                     <p>And ſeveral Grants and Promiſes made of Fines and Forfeitures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Conviction or Judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſons upon whom the ſame were to be levied.</p>
                     <p>All which are utterly and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to the known Laws and Statutes, and Freedom of this Realm.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the late King <hi>James</hi> the Second, having <hi>abdicated</hi> the Government, and the Throne being thereby <hi>vacant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (whom it hath pleaſed Almighty God to make the Glorious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Delivering this Kingdom from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi>) did (by the Advice of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and divers principal Perſons of the Commons) cauſe Letters to be written to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proteſtants, and other Letters to the ſeveral Counties, Cities, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, Burroughs, Cinque-Ports for the chuſing of ſuch Perſons to repreſent them, as were of right to be ſent to Parliament, to meet and ſit at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> upon the 22d day
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41262:33"/>of <hi>January,</hi> 1688, in order to ſuch an Eſtabliſhment, as that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Laws and Liberties, might not again be in danger of being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; upon which Letters Elections have been accordingly made.</p>
                     <p>And thereupon the ſaid Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, purſuant to their Reſpective Letters and Elections, being now Aſſembled in a full and Free <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative</hi> of this Nation, taking into their moſt ſerious conſideration the beſt means for attaining the Ends aforeſaid, do in the firſt place (as their Anceſtors in like caſe have uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally done) for the vindicating and aſſerting their Ancient Rights and Liberties, declare,</p>
                     <p>That the pretended Power of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending of Laws, or the Execution of Laws, by Regal Authority, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of Parliament, is il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal.</p>
                     <p>That the pretended Power of Diſpenſing with Laws, or the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Laws by Regal Authority, as it hath been aſſumed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed of late, is illegal.</p>
                     <p>That the Commiſſion for erecting the late <hi>Court of Commiſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes,</hi> and all other Commiſſions and Courts of the like nature, are illegal and pernicious.</p>
                     <p>That Levying of Money to, or for the uſe of the Crown, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Prerogative, without Grant of Parliament, for longer time, or in other manner, than the ſame is, or ſhall be Granted, is illegal.</p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41262:33"/>
                     <p>That it is the Right of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to Petition the King, and all Commitments and Proſecutions for ſuch Petitioning are illegal.</p>
                     <p>That the raiſing or keeping a ſtanding Army within the Kingdom in time of Peace, unleſs it be by conſent of Parliament, is againſt Law.</p>
                     <p>That the Subjects being Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, may have Arms for their Defence ſuitable to their condition, and as allowed by Law.</p>
                     <p>That the Election of Members of Parliament ought to be Free.</p>
                     <p>That the freedom of Speech, and Debates, or Proceedings in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought not to be impeached or queſtioned in any Court, or Place out of Parliament.</p>
                     <p>That Exceſſive Bail ought not to be required, nor Exceſſive Fines impoſed, nor cruel and unuſual Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments inflicted.</p>
                     <p>That Jurors ought to be duly Impannell'd and Returned, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which paſs upon men in Trials for High-Treaſon ought to be Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders.</p>
                     <p>That all Grants and Promiſes of Fines and Forfeitures of particular perſons before Conviction, are ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and void.</p>
                     <p>And that for Redreſs of all Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances; and for the amending, ſtrengthning, and preſerving of the Laws, Parliaments ought to be held frequently.</p>
                     <p>And they do claim, demand, and inſiſt upon all and ſingular the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as their undoubted Rights
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41262:34"/>and Liberties; and that no Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Judgments, Doings, or Proceedings, to the prejudice of the people in any of the ſaid Premiſes, ought in any wiſe to be drawn hereafter into Conſequence or Example.</p>
                     <p>To which demand of their Rights, they are particularly encouraged by the Declaration of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as being the only means for obtaining a full Redreſs and Remedy therein.</p>
                     <p>Having therefore an intire Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that his ſaid Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will perfect the Deliverance ſo far advanced by him, and will ſtill preſerve them from the violation of their Rights, which they have here aſſerted, and from all other Attempts upon their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Rights and Liberties;</p>
                     <p>The ſaid Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Weſtminſter, <hi>do Reſolve,</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY, Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> be, and be declared King and Queen of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, to hold the Crown and Royal Dignity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions, to them the ſaid Prince and Princeſs during their Lives, and the Life of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivor of them; and that the ſole and full exerciſe of the Regal Power be only in, and executed by the ſaid Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in the Names of the ſaid Prince and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41262:34"/>Princeſs during their joynt Lives; and after their Deceaſes, the ſaid Crown and Royal Dignity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions to be to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid Princeſs; and for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the Heirs of her Body; and for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And the ſaid Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, do pray the ſaid Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> to accept the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
                     <p>And that the Oaths hereafter mentioned, be taken by all perſons of whom the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance and</hi> Supremacy might be required by Law inſtead of them; and that the ſaid Oarhs of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> be abrogated.</p>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I A. B.</hi> Do ſincerely Promiſe and Swear, That I will be Faithful, and bear true Allegiance to Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>So help me God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I A. B.</hi> Do Swear, That I do from my Heart Abbor, Deteſt, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure, as Impious and Heretical, this Damnable Doctrine and Poſition, <hi>That Princes Excommunicated or Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Pope, or any Authority of the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>may be depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever.</hi> And I do
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41262:35"/>declare, That no Foreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Prcheminence or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>So help me God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Jo. Brown,</hi> Cler. Parliamentor.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The ſame day this Declaration bears date, Her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> arrived in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Thames</hi> in the Afternoon, and was received with all the Hearty Demonſtrations and Expreſſions of Joy by the City, that are uſual on ſuch occaſions.</p>
               <p>The <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> the Lords and Commons ordered the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Proclamation to be publiſhed and made.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WHereas it hath pleaſed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in his great Mercy to this Kingdom, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe us a miraculous Deliverance from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> and that our Preſervation is due, next under God, to the Reſolution and Conduct of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whom God hath choſen to be the Glorious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch an ineſtimable Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us and our Poſterity: And being highly ſenſible, and fully perſuaded of the great and eminent Virtues of Her Highneſs the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> whoſe Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, will no doubt bring a Bleſſing along with Her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41262:35"/>this Nation. And whereas the Lords and Commons now aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> have made a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preſented the ſame to the ſaid Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> and therein deſired Them to accept the Crown; who have accepted the ſame accordingly. We therefore the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, together with the Lord Mayor and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and others of the Commons of this Realm, do with full conſent publiſh and proclaim, according to the ſaid Declaration, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY,</hi> Prince and Princeſs of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> to be KING and QUEEN of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> wit all the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging: Who are accordingly ſo to be owned, deemed, and taken, by all the people of the aforeſaid Realms and Dominions, who are from hence-forward bound to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and pay unto them, all Faith and true Allegiance; Beſeeching God, by whom Kings reign, to Bleſs King <hi>VVilliam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> with long and happy Years to reign over us.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>God ſave King <hi>VVilliam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary, John Brown,</hi> Clericus Parliamentorum.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41262:5"/>
               <head>Some Clergy-mens Ways of Diſpoſing of Them.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Diſcourſe of God's Ways of Diſpoſing of Kingdoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Promotion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But God is the Judge; He putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TWO things the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſhews in the words of this Text. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The true Original of Power. This in <hi>David</hi>'s time all men took
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41262:6"/>to be from Heaven, but from whom there, many knew not. The <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Nations, who were generally given to Aſtrology, took it to come from their Stars; and eſpecially from the Sun, which was the chief Object of their Worſhip. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells them, No. <hi>Promotion cometh not</hi> that way: Neither from the Planets ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, nor ſetting, nor from its exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in Mid-Heaven. That's the meaning of the words, <hi>from the Eaſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">But Wiſe-men come out of the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> tho' Promotion come from the <hi>North:</hi> They are not Country-men.</note> 
                     <hi>nor from the Weſt, nor from the South.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the <hi>North</hi> of the Zodiac, or from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the hidden part under the Horizon, they never thought it to come. And (as ſome think) that's the reaſon why that part of Heaven is not mention'd.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> might have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon to himſelf, why he did not think fit to ſay, it comes not from the <hi>North.</hi> For there (as he ſaith elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) <hi>on the North-ſide</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was <hi>Mount Sion, the City of the great King</hi> of Heaven and Earth. There in <hi>David</hi>'s time was the Tabernacle, and afterwards there was the Temple, in which the Mercy-ſeat between the Cherubims was the place of the Symbolical Preſence of God. <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>could <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>Promotion</hi> comes not from thence? No, he ſaith the contrary in the following words; <hi>for God is the Judge:</hi> plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that to him Kings owe their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41262:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is to him as <hi>Judge.</hi> He gives it Judicially. And ſo to him they are to account for it. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>'Tis the Prerogative of God, by which He acts, both in the diſpoſing, and alſo in the transferring of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
                  <p>The word God in bringing His Majeſty into this Kingdom, was truly God's making uſe of the latter branch of his Prerogative, <hi>in putting down one, and ſetting up another.</hi> p. 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Powers that be, are of God:</hi> That is, the ſeveral Kingdoms and States, even all that are in the World, all have their Authority from God.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. This at firſt was from God, we are ſure, becauſe it was from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Mankind. The firſt Men that were born into the World, were all of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Family. <hi>p.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noah</hi> was the Father of all them that liv'd after the Flood.</p>
                  <p>When the Fathers or Heads of ſome of thoſe Nations made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts upon one another, as <hi>Nimrod</hi> did on the Nations about him, who was therefore call'd <hi>a mighty hunter before the Lord;</hi> or when they were otherwiſe incorporated together; theſe made the ancient great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, whereof the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> are famous in Ancient Hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>Other of thoſe Nations, or rather great Families, continu'd in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient way of Patriarchal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Particularly in that Line out of which God choſe his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>a mighty Prince</hi> in his days: But all his Subjects were of his Family, out of which proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>many Nations.</hi> From his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41262:7"/>there came <hi>two Nations of People;</hi> one of them by <hi>Eſau,</hi> Father of <hi>Edom,</hi> the other by <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Father of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who for their times alſo govern'd thoſe Families or Nations.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Jacob</hi> and all his Family went down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> there ended their Patriarchal Government. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, being Subjects to the King of that Country, they were brought into a long and ſore Bondage, which <hi>made their Lives bitter to them</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Generations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From this God deliver'd them by the hand of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And to ſhew them how they ought to value this mercy, from thence he entitled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be their King, and dated the beginning of his Reign.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This <hi>Theocracy,</hi> as we call it, continu'd from their coming up out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> till ſuch time as God, at his Peoples deſire, gave them <hi>a King to judge them like all the Nations. p.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>God was pleas'd ſo far to grant his Peoples Requeſt, that they ſhould be an Hereditary Kingdom: But for the firſt King of the reigning Line,<note place="margin">I thought the People had choſen him by lot. at <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pah.</hi>
                     </note> God would have the chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him himſelf. And accordingly, firſt he choſe <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then God made choice of <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">I thought the People had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>David</hi> too.</note> a man <hi>after his own heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was no other ſtanding Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in that Nation, which God choſe to be his peculiar People, but what was adminiſtred by ſingle Perſons. And thoſe Perſons Title to the Government was either Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchal,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41262:7"/>or by Divine nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Both which ways of coming into Power were ſo wholly of God, that the People had nothing to do, but to accept the Choice of God, and to ſubmit to it.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. In other Nations indeed, that did not keep up the Patriarchal Right, there the Peoples Conſent was required, except in the Caſe of Conqueſt. <hi>p.</hi> 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>And this Conſent being merely an humane Act, it may ſeem that the Authority it gives, is not, as we are here taught, from God only.</p>
                  <p>But we are to conſider by what Motives it is, that the People are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally led, to chuſe any one to rule over them. All their Motives may be reduc'd to theſe two; either Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or Favour. If there be any other, they are but Compoſitions of theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. The firſt Choice of Kings I conceive to have been made on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Merit, the People being led to it by a ſenſe of the Benefits they had receiv'd. I judge ſo from that which having been already ſhewn, I take now for granted, that the Earth was peopled at firſt by great Families. Now when thoſe, by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of powerful Neighbours, or by Civil Diſcord among themſelves, came to be in great diſtreſs, ſuch as made them ſee the neceſſity of being united in greater Bodies for their own preſervation; thoſe Heroic Men, that ſhew'd them the way of it, and that brought them under Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Laws, theſe were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the FOUNDERS of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Such was <hi>Moſes</hi> among the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41262:8"/>People of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> When he had brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they own'd this as a Title to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he would have had, even without Divine Nomination. Such was <hi>Cecrops</hi> among the <hi>Athanians,</hi> and <hi>Romulus</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> and other firſt Kings in other Nations. <hi>p.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>Next to theſe, and ſomething like them, were the firſt Planters of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies: Such as <hi>Cadmus</hi> was at <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Latium,</hi> and the like. In <hi>England</hi> ſuch were <hi>Hengiſt,</hi> and the reſt that began the Seven Kingdoms of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Heptarchy. From one of theſe, namely,<note place="margin">But not in the Right Line, Sir, under fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</note> from <hi>Cerdic,</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> the Deſcent of our Royal Family is unqueſtionable.</p>
                  <p>But the moſt like to Founders are they whom God raiſes up to be the Reſtorers and Delivers of a People, when they are either brought low by Tyranny and Oppreſſion, or when they are torn in pieces by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions among themſelves. <hi>p. 12, 13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus when the <hi>Roman</hi> State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing torn by a long Civil War, had even bled it ſelf to death, (it had certainly expir'd, if it had been left to it ſelf) <hi>Auguſtus</hi> came in, and not only bound up the Wounds, but put, as it were, a new Soul into the Body; He made it not only live, but flouriſh, by his great Care and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Induſtry; which ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd the People, that they even forc'd him to accept of the Empire. Theſe were ſuch Benefits to Mankind, as whoſoever was enabled to do, it was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41262:8"/>as if God had put a Glory about his Head; it ſo markt him out to the People, that they could not go beſide him in their Choice;<note place="margin">No; they took him as a ſucceſsful Tyrant, whom they had not power to withſtand. The <hi>Romans</hi> did not underſtand our new-coin'd Choice of God. And if our Regency-men had known that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was choſen of God, they would not have voted as they did.</note> they took him as one already cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen of God. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>In thoſe Kingdoms wherein the Succeſſion is continued by a new Election upon every Vacancy, or wherein a new Election is made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Extinguiſhing of the Royal Family, the perſon on whom the Election falls in either caſe, owes his promotion to God, from whom it comes the ſame way to him, as it came to his firſt Predeceſſor in that Kingdom. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>In all ſorts of Government, as the Sovereign Power in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey or Nation is of God, ſo they that are inveſted with it, whether one or many, are in the place of God, and have their <hi>Promotion</hi> from him.</p>
                  <p>The Transferring of this Power from one to another, is the Act of God. And this he does, proceeding Judicially, as being <hi>Judge. p.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, God does this: Secondly, He does it Judicially.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of theſe, God has ſuch an Intereſt in the diſpoſing of power, as none can pretend to but himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Men have their part in ſetting up
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41262:9"/>what they cannot put down again. It is a Woman's Conſent makes a Man be her Husband; the Fellows of a College chuſe one to the their Head; a Corporation chuſe one to be their Mayor: All theſe do only chuſe the perſon, they do not give him the Authority. It is the Law that gives that, and that Law ſo binds their hands, that they cannot undo what they have done.</p>
                  <p>No more can a Nation undo its own Act, in chuſing Men into So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign power. I do not ſay but they may chuſe Men into Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, expreſly with that Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That they ſhall be accountable to the people; and then the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment remains in the Body of the Nation, it is that which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call a Commonwealth. But for Sovereign Princes and Kings, even where they are choſen by the Nation; and much more in Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Kingdoms; as they have their Authority from God, ſo they are only accountable to him. For he is <hi>the only Potentate, King of king, and Lord of lords.</hi> He alone both makes Kings by his Sovereign Power, and by the ſame he can unmake them when he pleaſes. <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19.</p>
                  <p>Nay, more than ſo, <hi>He puts down one, and ſets up another.</hi> Both the Words imply ſomething of an high place, and here they are uſed of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government or Dominion. Of this it is ſaid, That God ſo deprives one of it, as that he advances ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his ſtead.</p>
                  <p>This can be underſtood of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the Conqueſt of one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41262:9"/>Prince over another. For what one reſigns by a Voluntary Act, he is ſaid to lay down, or to give it up to another. But <hi>putting down</hi> is the Act of a Superior, by which one's place is taken from him againſt his Will. Now God being the Superior that does this by the Act of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, it muſt be ſuch an Act as gives the Power from <hi>one</hi> againſt his Will, to <hi>another</hi> whom God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſet up in his ſtead. Thus in giving <hi>one</hi> Prince a Conqueſt over <hi>another,</hi> he thereby puts one in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the other's Dominions, he makes the other's Subjects become his Subjects, or his Slaves, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly as they come in upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or at the Will of the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. In ſhort, he giveth him the whole Right and Power of the other Prince. <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19, 20.</p>
                  <p>When thoſe Kings, that living in a <hi>ſettled Kingdom,</hi> will not govern according to the Laws thereof; it is a breach of Faith, not only to their people, but to God alſo, where they are ſworn to the obſerving of Laws. And though they are not therefore to be depoſed by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet they cannot eſcape the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, who ordinarily pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes them with the natural effects of their Sin.</p>
                  <p>On the other hand, if a Prince will have no law but his Will, if he tramples and oppreſſeth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their patience will not hold out always, they will at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew themſelves to be but Men. At leaſt they will have no heart to fight for their Oppreſſor, So that if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41262:10"/>a Foreign Enemy breaks in upon him, he is gone without remedy, unleſs God interpoſe. But how can that be, when <hi>God is Judge</hi> himſelf? Should the Judge hinder the doing of Juſtice? It is God's Work that Foreigners come to do, <hi>Howbeit he meaneth not ſo.</hi> He means nothing, perhaps, but the ſatisfying of his own Luſt. But though he knoweth it not; he is ſent in God's Meſſage; for which all things being prepared by Natural Cauſes, and God not hindering his own Work, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haſtning it; no wonder that it ſucceeds, and that oftentimes very eaſily. <hi>p.</hi> 24, 25.</p>
                  <p>When it happens (as it doth ſometimes, and that eſpecially for the Sins of a Nation), that they come to be under weak or wicked Kings; even theſe they muſt not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,</hi> God hath taught them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. What then? Muſt they be left to the Wills of theſe Tyrants? Or of them that govern weak Kings, which is commonly worſe? Muſt they endure all the load of Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that theſe will lay upon them? That is, For a few Mens pleaſure, muſt a Nation be made miſerable? This is far from God's deſign in the Inſtitution of Government. He makes Kings his <hi>Miniſters for the good</hi> of their People. If any will take that Office upon them, they muſt be have themſelves accordingly. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if they take it as given them only for themſelves, it is ſuch a breach of Truſt, that God cannot but puniſh them for it. But how ſhould he do this, ſo as that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41262:10"/>puniſhment may have its effect, in warning others not to tranſgreſs in like manner? He cannot do this bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than by making Men his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in it. And therefore it is that God, tho he has infinite ways, yet commonly chuſes to employ Men in this Service. He either finds them at home, that are <hi>not afraid of the Power, as they ought to be;</hi> or he brings them in from Foreign Countries, <hi>Whiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the Fly out of Egypt, or the Bee out of the land of Aſſyria:</hi> In plain words, ſtirring up a <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or a <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> againſt them. God may employ ſuch if he will, tho none is too good for this work, to execute his righteous Judgments. And when God doth his work by their hands, whatſoever the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be, the Cauſe being ſo juſt, and ſo evident as we have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; <hi>All men that ſee it, will ſay, Doubtleſs there is a God that judges on the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the way of <hi>Juſtice,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">But the Pr. of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> was not a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; being diſpoſſeſt of his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality.</note> God acts as a <hi>judge</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Two Sovereign Powers, when they bring their Cauſes before him; that is, when they make War upon one another. And when he ſeeth his time, that is, when he finds the Cauſe ripe for Judgment, if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds ſo far, then he gives Sentence for him that is injur'd, againſt him that hath done the Injury. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this Sentence is a juſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; and that is the other way in which God, proceeding judicially, <hi>pats down one, and ſets up another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41262:11"/>
                  <p>That this may be the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, there are four things to be conſider'd particularly.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That War is an Appeal to the Juſtice of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That none can be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to this, but they that are in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Power.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That to make it a juſt War, there muſt be a juſt and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That Conqueſt in ſuch a War, is a deciſive Judgment of God, and gives <hi>one</hi> a Right to the Dominions that he has conquered from the <hi>others.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That War is an Appeal to God; this appears in the nature of the thing. <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>The Parties to this Appeal, are properly ſuch as have no Superior but God. For them that have an earthly Superior, their Appeal lies to him as <hi>God's Miniſter, attending con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually on this very thing. p.</hi> 29.</p>
                  <p>Subjects have no Right to make War, without the leave of their Princes. For as God has given Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the power of the Sword, ſo he forbids it to Subjects, under a great Penalty, <hi>They that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword.</hi> And if he has not admitted them to be Parties in his Court, then it is certain that they cannot ſue there; or if they do, they can acquire no Flight by it. There is an Original Nullity in all their Proceedings.</p>
                  <p>As none have right of making War, but they that are in Sovereign Power, ſo neither is it given to them that they may make what uſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41262:11"/>of it they pleaſe: Particularly, they muſt not make War for the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Luſts, Ambition, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Vain-glory, or the like. Nay, the righteous God will not hold him guiltleſs that hath Juſtice in his Cauſe, and yet in his Heart hath no ſuch thing. Lawful things muſt be done lawfully. This Princes muſt look to, as they will anſwer it to God.</p>
                  <p>But as far as man can judge, it is a Lawful War that is made for a juſt and ſufficient Cauſe. <hi>p.</hi> 32. 33.</p>
                  <p>One Prince may make War in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of another King's Subjects, if they ſee themſelves in extreme dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuffering an intolerable Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by his Oppreſſion of his own people. And in theſe caſes, if one Lawfully may, then it is certain he ought to do it. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</p>
                  <p>They are ſo much the more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to this, when it is evident, that the threatning miſchief is like to fall upon others, as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and them, ſuch as they are bound in Honour and Conſcience to protect and ſupport. When by fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill they ſhould certainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not only themſelves to be ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but alſo their Friends and Allies to periſh with them; in that caſe, <hi>Saevitia eſt voluiſſe mori,</hi> it is a ſort of bloody Peaceableneſs, it is cruelty to Mankind to go to that degree of ſuffering Injuries.</p>
                  <p>But eſpecially, when the Cauſe of God is concern'd, to whom we owe all things, and ought to venture all for his ſake. Surely 'tis his Cauſe, when it touches Religion; which is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41262:12"/>all that is dear to him in this world. And tho Religion it ſelf teaches us, <hi>if it be poſſible, as much as in us lies, to live peaceably with all man;</hi> yet as 'tis there ſuppoſed, there may be Cauſe to break the Peace; ſo it adds infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely to that Cauſe, when it comes to concern our Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 36, 37.</p>
                  <p>There is yet a greater Cauſe for this, when the Suffering-Religion is that which is eſtabliſh'd by the Laws of that Kingdom; and yet the King that is ſworn to thoſe Laws, and therefore bound to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that Religion, is manifeſtly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing againſt it, and endeavours to ſupplant, and oppreſs, and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it. What ſhould other Princes or States that profeſs the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, do in this caſe? They ſee that ſuch a King is ſet upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of their Religion. He hath declar'd a hoſtile mind towards the profeſſors of it, in judging them not capable of enjoying their Temporal Rights. If he deals thus with his own People, what are Foreigners to expect at his hands? Can they think themſelves ſecure, becauſe they are at peace with him? They cannot; unleſs Treaties are more Sacred than Laws. Or can they rely upon his Oath? But they ſee he hath broken it. And therefore they have reaſon to judge, That either he makes no Conſcience of an Oath, or he thinks Faith is not to be kept with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, or he hath a Superior that can diſpenſe with him, or that will abſolve him from the guilt of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury in ſuch caſes where Religion is concerned. In ſhort, they are ſure of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41262:12"/>his Will to deſtroy them, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſure of his Oath to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Wherein them can they be ſafe? But in his want of power to do them hurt? But he will not want power, if they let him go on, for he is getting it as faſt as he can. He is now ſtrengthning himſelf by thoſe ways that he takes to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Lord of his own people: And he is now weakning Them, by oppreſſing all thoſe among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom he knows to be their Friends and Well-wiſhers. He doth both theſe things together: He dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leſſens their party, and makes them as many more Enemies, as he gains Men over to his Religion. And if that be ſuch a Religion as pretends to a Right of deſtroying Men of other Religions; knowing this, they know what they are to expect. When this pretended Right is armed with power, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall upon them. So that they muſt begin before he is ready for them, or elſe it will be too late to do any thing for their own preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p>But as it is neceſſary for them to do this for themſelves, ſo they ought to do it much the rather for the ſakes of their oppreſſed Brethren: That, by a timely aſſerting of their own Right, they may alſo deliver them from the Evils they ſuffer at preſent, and ſave them from that Deſtruction which is coming upon them. As it was juſt and neceſſary on thoſe former Accounts, ſo this makes it a pious Cauſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more worthy of a true
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41262:13"/>Chriſtian Prince. It has been judg'd ſo by them whoſe Names we have in great Veneration. We have the Examples of our own Princes here in <hi>England,</hi> in the beſt of Times ſince the Reformation: Theſe the Reader may ſind collected to his hand, in an excellent Book that hath been lately publiſhed. But this may as well be ſhewn in the Example; of them whom our Princes choſe to follow as their Paterns; namely, of the Chriſtians in Primitive Times, and eſpecially at the time of the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. In theſe times we find that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhar'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, had paſſed a Decree together at <hi>Milan,</hi> for Chriſtianity to be the Eſtabliſhed Religion: And when afterward <hi>Licinius,</hi> in his part of the Empire, would have oppreſs'd it contrary to Law; for that cauſe <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great made War upon him; and in proſecution of that War, thruſt him out of his Empire: For which he was ſo far from being blamed by any Chriſtian in thoſe times, even by thoſe that had been <hi>Licinius</hi>'s Subjects, as moſt of thoſe Biſhops were, that ſate in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, that they all gave him the higheſt Praiſes and Encomiums, and bleſſed God that had ſent them that happy Deliverance by his means. <hi>Euſebius</hi> was <hi>Licinius</hi>'s Subject, and he afterwards writ the Life of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, in which they that pleaſe may read whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41262:13"/>
                  <p>As that is a juſt War which is made upon juſt and ſufficient Cauſe, ſo the Effect of ſuch a War, being a Conqueſt, is Juſt.</p>
                  <p>Conqueſt being the way by which a Kingdom or Dominion is taken from a Sovereign Prince againſt his Will, and by which another Prince gets it into his Poſſeſſion; as often as this happens, there ariſes a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion between the two Princes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them hath a Right to that Kingdom or Dominion.</p>
                  <p>For the deciding of this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it muſt be by ſuch a Law as is common to both the Parties, whoſe Rights are to be judg'd by it. That cannot be the Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; for tho the Prince that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiz'd, was obliged by that Law while he was in poſſeſſion, yet now it ſeems he is not; and it never was a Law to the Prince that is now in his place. It muſt therefore be a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Law, ſuch as is common to all Sovereign Princes in their Affairs with one another, and that (as hath been already ſhewn) is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily the Law of Nations.</p>
                  <p>I ſay ordinarily, becauſe there is yet a Superior Law, namely, the Law of God; whether written in our Hearts, which we commonly call the Law of Nature; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an expreſs Revelation from God, ſuch as was ſometimes given to Men in Ancient Times; either of theſe may derogate from the Law of Nations: For this, being made up of Cuſtoms obſerv'd by Princes and States among themſelves, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſubject to the will of him that is Lord of lords, and King of kings.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41262:14"/>But whether, or how far, this may alter the caſe, will be conſidered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; at preſent we are only to conſider what Judgment can be made of it, according to the Law of Nations.</p>
                  <p>By this it ſeems to be plain, That the Right ſhould go along with the compleat poſſeſſion: So as that whereſoever this is once ſettled, whether by length of time or even ſooner, by a general Conſent of the people, there it ought to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med there is a Right, at leaſt, there ought to be no farther Diſpute of it. There ſeems to be the ſame reaſon for this, that there is for the Law of Nations it ſelf; for if that Law was ordained for the peace of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, this quitting of poſſeſſion muſt be a part of it, for there can be no end of Wars otherwiſe. <hi>p.</hi> 45, 46, 47, <hi>to</hi> 51.</p>
                  <p>This appears by <hi>Jephtha</hi>'s Speech to the King of <hi>Ammon</hi> that had <hi>Chemoſh</hi> for his God; <hi>Wilt not thou poſſeſs that which</hi> Chemoſh <hi>thy God giveth thee to poſſeſs? So whomſoever the Lord our God ſhall drive out from before as, them will we poſſeſs. p.</hi> 51.</p>
                  <p>It is by way of Conqueſt, that God <hi>puts down one, and ſets up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> For ſo the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Empire was put down by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who ſet up the <hi>Perſian</hi> in its ſtead. The <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire was put down in their laſt King <hi>Darius,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> ſet up the <hi>Macedon</hi> in its ſtead. The <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Kingdom was put down in their laſt King <hi>Perſeus,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> was fet up in its ſtead.</p>
                  <p>All theſe Kingdoms were chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Conqueſts that they made
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41262:14"/>one upon another. And ſo it was by thoſe Conqueſts, that God <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Kings, and ſet up Kings. p.</hi> 53.</p>
                  <p>I do not ſay but they would have oppoſed the making of one of thoſe Conqueſts, namely, that of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, becauſe King <hi>Darius</hi> was then living. But when they ſaw they could not Oppoſe, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt being already made, then Juſt or Unjuſt, they ſubmitted to it; and having ſubmitted, they were ſubject without any more Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</p>
                  <p>Therefore alſo Juſt and Religious Kings have reckoned their Conqueſts among the great things that God wrought by their means; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted them as much their Subjects whom they had gain'd by the Sword, as them that were born in their Dominions.</p>
                  <p>Therefore alſo God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his people to give Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Kings that came in by Conqueſt, without any other Title. Nay, to ſuch as were capable of no other; for they were forbidden <hi>to ſet a ſtranger over them, which was not their brother.</hi> And yet they were Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to ſtrangers, ſuch as <hi>Cuſhan, Eglon,</hi> and <hi>Jabin,</hi> &amp;c. And in <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s time God commanded them upon pain of death, to become the Subjects of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who had made a full Conqueſt over them, and held their lawful King <hi>Jeconiab</hi> then in Captivity. This is plainly the Doctrine of that Convocation which ſate in the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> I. his time; and therefore it cannot but be very unjuſt, to charge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41262:15"/>any Man with Singularity or Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that goes in the ſteps of ſo many and ſo great Authors. <hi>p.</hi> 53, 54, 55.</p>
                  <p>But ſome Learned and Judicious Men think, That whereas an unjuſt Conqueſt happens through the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, for the puniſhing of a ſinful Prince or Nation; it doth not appear that he that is the Inſtrument of this, acquires any Right by it; more than thoſe Pirates or Robbers, who are inſtrumental likewiſe, in the puniſhing of inferior Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. And if God gives no Right to him whom he ſets up, then it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in him whom he has put down: So that he is rightful King ſtill, tho he is out of poſſeſſion, and the other is but an Uſurper that is in poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe, if the Uſurper has no pretence of Right, no preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time, no Conſent of the people, but only an unjuſt poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; how a Subject ought to behave himſelf towards him, even this is a <hi>Difficult Queſtion,</hi> in a moſt learned Man's Judgment: Who yet judges, That even here it may be not only Lawful, but a Duty, to obey him that is in poſſeſſion, when the Legal King is reduced to that paſs, that he can no more do the Office of a King to his people. For (ſaith he) the Kingdom cannot be without Government; and if the Uſurper preſerves the Kingdom, a Lover of his Countrey ought not (as things are) to give any further cauſe of trouble by his unprofitable Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. But then put caſe the Uſurper hath ſworn the people to him, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41262:15"/>doth the Office of a King, which (it ſeems) in his Judgment doth not take away the duty that is ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that former King; how one can pay his duty to both, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd Legal King, and to ſuch an Uſurper. This our Author ſays is <hi>a moſt difficult Scruple;</hi> and ſo it ſeems both by his, and our moſt Learned Caſuiſt's handling the Queſtion; where they ſhew how far one ought, and how far one ought not to comply with ſuch an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. <hi>p.</hi> 56, 57, 58.</p>
                  <p>But theſe Difficulties are only in caſe the poſſeſſion is obtained by a War that was certainly unjuſt; for if the cauſe of the War was but doubtful, and a Conqueſt follows upon it, there is no place for theſe difficulties: Much leſs where the cauſe of War was certainly Juſt; for if a Conqueſt follows upon this, it gives a Right, and then there is no Uſurpation.</p>
                  <p>It has been commonly judg'd by the Law of Nations, That the Right goes along with the Poſſeſſion. Of this we ſee Examples in every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution that happens in this or any other Kingdom. When a King is driven out with any colour of Right, the Neighbouring Princes and States make no great difficulty of applying themſelves to him that comes in his ſtead; wherein though perhaps they too much follow their own Intereſt, yet it cannot be ſaid that what they do is againſt the Law of Nations. But what ſhould Subjects do in this Caſe? Of this we have an Example in the People of God, when they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41262:16"/>paſs'd ſucceſſively under the Yoke of thoſe Four great Monarchs that were formerly mention'd. It is likely that each of thoſe Kings that got the Power over them, firſt declar'd the Cauſe of the War that he made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former Lords. In that Caſe, though they could not judge of the Cauſe, whether it was Juſt or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, yet no doubt they did well in adhering to him that was in preſent Poſſeſſion. <hi>p.</hi> 60, 61.</p>
                  <p>To a People that are in ſuch a caſe, it is no ſmall Comfort, that whatſoever doubt they may have of the Cauſe of the War, yet there is no doubt at all concerning their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There is nothing more certain than this, that they ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves, if they can do it lawfully. But it is lawful for them to forbear fighting, when they are unſatisfied of the Cauſe: And if their own prince is not able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, it is lawful for them to take protection elſewhere. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in caſe of Invaſion for a Cauſe which is juſt, for ought they know, it is lawful for them to live quietly under the Invader: nay, it is not only lawful, but their duty (as hath been already ſhewn) to acquieſce in his Government, when he cornes to be in Poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>But when they are certain that a War is made upon their Prince for juſt Cauſe; that is, when they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee he hath drawn it upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by making it not only lawful, but neceſſary for another Prince to invade him for his own Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; What are the People to do in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41262:16"/>this Caſe? No doubt they ought firſt to have a care of their Souls, and not to endanger them by being Partakers of other mens Sins. They cannot but ſee, that, by engaging in the War, they abet their own Prince in his Injuſtice; though not in his doing the Injury, yet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing what is done, and in his not giving Reparation. And therefore they are ſubject to the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with him. Nay their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is worſe than his: For he may ſhift for himſelf, and leave them, and all they have, to be a Prey to the Enemy: Who by right of War may do with them and theirs what he pleaſes. It is therefore certainly their wiſeſt Courſe to keep themſelves free from all offence, both towards God, and towards Man: That having had no part in the Cauſe of the War, they may not be involv'd in the ill Conſequences of it. And this they have reaſon to expect from a Generous Enemy, that he will not uſe the Right of War againſt them that deſire to live peaceably. Much more, if he hath declar'd he would not hurt them that ſhould not reſiſt him, they have reaſon to truſt a juſt Prince upon his Declaration. And if he went ſo far as to declare, That upon their Submiſſion they ſhould enjoy the benefit of their own Laws; then, although it ſhould come to a Conqueſt, they may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect to be in no worſe condition under the Stranger, than they were under their own Prince: They have his Faith engaged to them for this.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41262:17"/>
                  <p>But if the Stranger declares he makes War in defence of another King's Subjects, as (we have ſhewn) he may lawfully do, when he finds himſelf in danger of ſuffering by that King's Oppreſſion of his own People; in this Caſe, they are firſt to conſider, whether it is a mere pretence, or whether there be a real ground for his Declaration. If they find there is a juſt and ſufficient ground for it, they ſee in effect, that it is through Them that he is ſtruck at; and therefore the War is not ſo much His, as their own. It is true according to our Doctrine, they are united to their Prince as a Wife to her Husband; ſo that they can no more right themſelves by Arms, than ſhe can ſue her Husband while the Bond of Marriage conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues. Yet as, When her Husband uſes her extremely ill, ſhe may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of him to the Judge, who, if he ſees Cauſe, may diſſolve the Marriage by his Sentence; and after that ſhe is at liberty to ſue him as well as any other Man: So a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may cry to the Lord by reaſon of their Oppreſſion, and he may raiſe them up a Deliverer, that ſhall take the Government into his hands (a Foreign Prince may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do this, as hath been already ſhewn) and then they are not only free to defend themſelves, but are oblig'd to join with him, againſt their Oppreſſor. <hi>p.</hi> 62, 63, 64, 65.</p>
                  <p>In this Caſe, if another Prince, having a juſt Cauſe of War, is ſo far concern'd for ſuch a People, as to take them into his Care, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41262:17"/>that he makes the War for their Deliverance: The effect of this War, though we may call it a Conqueſt, becauſe it has reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of it, yet it cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo in any reſpect; whether we conſider the Prince on whom it is made, or the People that have their Deliverance by it.</p>
                  <p>As to him, it is properly an <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> by the juſt Sentence of God; who thus puts him out of a Truſt, that he abuſed, to the hurt of them for whoſe ſakes it was given him. And as to the people, it cannot be a Conqueſt over them, who are ſo far from having the War made againſt them, that it was made chiefly for their ſakes. If there be any pretence of a Conqueſt, it is only over them that were their Oppreſſors. <hi>p.</hi> 66, 67.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Matter in diſpute is not whether <hi>Rightful, Lawful Kings are to be obeyed,</hi> but who in our preſent Circumſtances is our Rightful, Lawful Sovereign; not whether <hi>Kings be not God's Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> but whether God doth not ſometimes confer the Right of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty by a <hi>Law ſuperiour</hi> to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>particular Countries,</hi> that is, by the <hi>Law of Nations,</hi> which eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth ſuch a <hi>Right</hi> upon the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of a Juſt War; not <hi>whether Sovereign Princes are not accountable only to God,</hi> but whether Allegiance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41262:18"/>be not due where the Rights of Sovereignty are placed, by an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Act of Providence,</hi> and the <hi>concurrent Conſent of the Nation.</hi> p. 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>We muſt of neceſſity look back to the Occaſions of this great Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: And there were two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Occaſions of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Great and violent Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an Injury to the Right of Succeſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Too great Evidences of a formed Deſign to ſubvert the Eſtabliſhed Religion and Civil Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>Now there are two very mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Queſtions which ariſe from hence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether theſe were the <hi>juſt Occaſions</hi> of a War.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether upon the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this War, the <hi>Rights of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty</hi> were duly transferred?</p>
                  <p>If theſe were <hi>juſt Occaſions</hi> of a War, and upon the Succeſs thereof the <hi>Sovereignty</hi> was duly transferred, then there can be no Diſpute left, to whom our Allegiance is due.</p>
                  <p>It is taken for granted by all who underſtand theſe Matters, That as there is a <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines the Rights and Properties of particular Nations; and that all private Perſons are bound to ſubmit to the Municipal Laws of thoſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties for their Peace and Security: So there are other Laws which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thoſe <hi>Nations,</hi> as they make up ſeveral <hi>independent Governments</hi> upon each other. And there are ſeveral
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41262:18"/>Rights which belong to them with reſpect to one another, which do not belong to private Perſons as they live in ſubjection to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Government.</p>
                  <p>And as there are ſuch Rights, ſo there muſt be a juſt and lawful way for reparation of Injuries. In par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Governments, the thing is plain by Eſtabliſhed Laws and Courts of Judicature, whoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is executed by the Civil Power; but in Separate Nations, and Independent Governments, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be Laws by conſent, called the <hi>Law of Nations;</hi> yet there is no common Judicature to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of Right and Wrong; and therefore in caſe of Injury, there is an allowance for the injured Party by this <hi>Law of Nations</hi> to right him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by force, as there would be to every particular Perſon, if there were no Laws nor Power to ſee them executed.</p>
                  <p>There is then a Right in every Sovereign and Independent Prince to exerciſe Force againſt another Prince, who detains any Right from him, or doth any Injury to him, or to thoſe he is bound to defend.</p>
                  <p>The Queſtion then comes to the <hi>Juſt Occaſions</hi> of ſuch a War; and here are two aſſigned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Great and violent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions of an Injury to the Right of Succeſſion. This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mentioned and inſiſted on, in the Declaration of the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (our preſent King.) <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41262:19"/>
                  <p>There have been many Inſtances in Hiſtory of ſuborned and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitious Princes, and therefore there was reaſon that ſufficient Evidence ſhould be given in a Caſe of ſuch Importance, and which was under ſo great Suſpicion. But if there was no reaſonable care taken to prevent or remove theſe Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious, then the Parties moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned have a right to aſſert their own Pretenſions in ſuch a way as the Law of Nations doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
                  <p>And in this Caſe no private Depoſitions, or confident Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of ſuch as are Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or otherwiſe liable to Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion, can in reaſon be taken for ſatisfactory Evidence. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> There was a further Juſt Occaſion for that Expedition, which was the Deſign to ſubvert our Religion and Civil Liberties. As to the Particulars, they are fully ſet down in the Declaration, and need not to be repeated; That which I am to make out, is, That the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> by his Relation to the Crown, had a juſt Right to concern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Vindication of both, and that this is not repugnant to the Doctrines and Principles of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was not thought diſagreeable to them for Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> againſt the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> yet ſhe had no ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it as our King and Queen had to prevent the ſuppreſſion of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41262:19"/>their own Religion here, and the Rights of that people to whom they were ſo nearly related. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, when I ſuppoſe it will be granted,<note place="margin">☜</note> That the Doctrines and Principles of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were underſtood and followed; the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had taken up Arms, <hi>to ſettle the Peace and liberty of</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, as he declared: But he met with a great Defeat. Whereupon King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf concerned to give Aſſiſtance to him: And Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was then employed (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth) by the King's Command, to draw up a <hi>Declaration,</hi> to be publiſhed in all the Pariſhes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which was read by the King, and approved by the Council, wherein the <hi>Greatneſs of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they were in is ſet forth, and the People are exhorted to ſerve God and the King, and to labour by their Prayers to divert the Danger.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lay this Danger? It is there ſaid to be, <hi>That by the Defeat of the King of</hi> Denmark, <hi>there was lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing left to hinder the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria <hi>from being Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of</hi> Germany. And what then? Why then <hi>there will be an open way for</hi> Spain <hi>to do what they pleaſed in all the Weſt Part of Chriſtendom.</hi> It ſeems then, it was not thought diſagreeable to the Principles and Doctrines of our Church, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth of a Weſtern Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, although it be by aſſiſting
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41262:20"/>Subjects againſt their Princes who promote it. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>But yet here is another Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty ariſeth, concerning the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Allegiance from a Lawful Prince, to him that met with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Succeſs in his Deſign.</p>
                  <p>And here I ſhall endeavour to make it plain, That this is not againſt the <hi>Doctrines and Principles of the Church of</hi> England. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Articles</hi> of our Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That the chief Government of all Eſtates of this Realm doth appertain to the Civil Magiſtrate:</hi> But they no-where ſay, That in a Juſt war the Superior Power cannot be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; or that God doth never confer it in an extraordinary me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
                  <p>The Book of <hi>Homilies</hi> is very ſevere againſt <hi>Diſobedience</hi> and <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rebellion;</hi> but it is no-where ſaid, That where the Right of Sovereignty is transferred by a Succeſsful War, there is no Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance due to thoſe who poſſeſs it. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ours is only the Caſe of Juſt War;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜ Apage nugas!</note> which is allowed by all ſorts of <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> who do agree, that Allegiance is due to the Party that prevails in it; and if it be due to one, it cannot be due to another, at the ſame time, although he be living, and do not diſcharge Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from their Oaths; for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of Oaths depends on the nature and reaſon of things, and not upon the Pleaſure of thoſe to whom they are made. But where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41262:20"/>there is a Right to govern, there muſt be a Duty of Allegiance: And that <hi>Succeſs in a Juſt War</hi> doth give <hi>ſuch a Right,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">What Right do you mean?</note> I could produce ſo many Teſtimonies, of all kinds of Writers, as would make the reading of them as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, as of thoſe in the Hiſtory of <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi> Nay, ſome go ſo far, as to aſſert a Right of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty to be acquired by ſucceſs, even in an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt War:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">So 'tis, as much as by a Juſt War.</note> But we need none of theſe Teſtimonies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But doth not all this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this whole Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie into a Right of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">'Tis not a pin-matter whether it does or no.</note> 
                     <hi>which is not ſo much as pretended in our preſent Caſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">It's a fine thing to be a Schollar.</note>I anſwer, That we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Right to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and the <hi>Manner of Aſſuming it.</hi> The <hi>Right</hi> was founded on the <hi>Juſt Cauſes</hi> of the War, and the Succeſs in it: But the aſſuming of it was not by any ways of force or violence, but by a Free <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> who by a <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Recognition,</hi> and Their Majeſties acceptance of the Government, as it is ſetled by our Laws, take away any pretence<note n="*" place="margin">But not to an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Whimſie of an imaginary Right by the Choice of God.</note> to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over the People, or a Government by Force.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41262:21"/>
                  <head>The Caſe of the Allegiance due to Sovereign Powers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THAT which has perplexed this Controverſie, is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixing the Diſpute of <hi>Right,</hi> with the Duty of <hi>Obedience,</hi> or making the <hi>Legal Right</hi> of Princes to their Thrones the only Reaſon and Foundation of <hi>the Allegiance</hi> of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: That <hi>Allegiance</hi> is due only to <hi>Right,</hi> not to <hi>Government,</hi> though it can be paid only to Government.</p>
                  <p>It ſeems to me to be unfit to diſpute the Right of Princes; a thing which no Government can permit to be a Queſtion among their Subjects. <hi>p.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I ſhall not meddle with this Diſpute, as being both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove me, and<note n="*" place="margin">Then you'll ſay nothing to the purpoſe.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my preſent purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Subjects have a plain Rule of Duty without underſtanding Laws and Politicks, the Intrigues of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Revolutions of States, the Diſputes of Princes; which I am ſure is both for the ſecurity of Governments and Subjects.</p>
                  <p>If then Allegiance be due, not for the ſake of Legal Right, but Government.</p>
                  <p>If Allegiance be due, not to bare Legal Right, but<note n="*" place="margin">That is, to Glergy-mens Crockets.</note> to the Authority of of God.</p>
                  <p>If God, when he ſees fit, and can better ſerve the ends of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence by it, ſets up Kings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to Legal Right or Humane Laws. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41262:21"/>
                  <p>If Kings, thus ſet up by God, are inveſted with God's Authority, which muſt be obey'd, not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</p>
                  <p>If theſe Principles be true, it is plain, That Subjects are bound to obey, and to pay and ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (if it be required) to thoſe Princes whom God hath placed and ſettled in the Throne, whatever Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes there may be about their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right, when they are inveſted with God's Authority.</p>
                  <p>And then it is plain, That our old Allegiance and old Oaths are at an end, when God has ſet over us a new King: For when God tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Kingdoms, and requires our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Allegiance to a new King, he neceſſarily transfers our Allegiance too.</p>
                  <p>This Scheme of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment may ſtartle ſome men at firſt,<note place="margin">From you it will ſtartle no man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have well conſidered it. <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> has been very careful to inſtruct Her Children in their Duty to Princes; to obey their Laws, and ſubmit to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and not to reſiſt, tho very inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly oppreſſed; and thoſe, who renounce theſe Principles, renounce the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> But ſhe has withal taught, That all Sovereign Princes receive their Power and Authority from God; and therefore every Prince who is ſetled in the Throne, is to be obey'd and reverenced as God's Miniſter, and to be reſiſted;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41262:22"/>which directs us what to do in all Revolutions of Government, when once they come to a Settlement; and thoſe who refuſe to pay and ſwear Allegiance to ſuch Princes, whom God has placed in the Throne, whatever then Legal Right be, do as much reject the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as thoſe who teach the Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Princes.</p>
                  <p>For the proof of which, I appeal to Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation-Book. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>I know not how it was poſſible for the Convocation to expreſs their ſenſe plainer, That all Uſurped Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when throughly ſettled, have God's Authority, and muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd: So that here are the Two great points determined, whereon this whole Controverſie turns.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That thoſe Princes who have no legal right to their Thrones, may yet have God's Authority.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That when they are through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſettled in their Thrones, they are inveſted with God's Authority, and muſt be reverenced and obeyed by all who live within their Territories and Dominions, as well Prieſts as People: If theſe propoſitions be true, it is a plain Reſolution of the Caſe; that if it ſhould at any time happen, that the rightful Prince ſhould be driven out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and another Prince placed in his Throne, and ſettled in the full Adminiſtration of Government, Subjects not only may, but muſt for Conſcience ſake, and out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41262:22"/>to the Authority of God, with which ſuch a Prince is inveſted, pay all the Duty and Allegiance of Subjects to him.</p>
                  <p>As for the firſt, the Caſe is plain, That the Convocation ſpeaks of il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal and uſurped Powers, and yet affirms that the Authority exerciſed by them, is God's Authority, and therefore thoſe Princes, who have no legal right, may have God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> never could have a Legal Right to the Government of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">What? not by a Conqueſt?</note> and yet the Convocation aſſerts, That when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in ſubjection to them, <hi>they knew, that it was not lawful for them of themſelves, and by their own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to take Arms againſt the Kings, whoſe Subjects they were,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prove they were Tyrants.</note> 
                     <hi>tho indeed they were Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like, they teach of the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon. p.</hi> 6</p>
                  <p>There is no Duty Subjects, as ſuch, owe to the moſt Legal and Rightful Kings, but the <hi>Convocation</hi> aſſerts due to all Kings, whom God hath placed in the Throne, by what viſible means ſoever they obtained it; as to obey and ſubmit to them, not to reſiſt them, nor rebel againſt them; to pay all Cuſtoms and Taxes, to pray for them, nay, to ſwear Allegiance to them, if it be required. <hi>p.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41262:23"/>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>only Enquiry</hi> then is,<note place="margin">No; it is no part of the Enquiry; for who cares what either they meant, or you mean?</note> what the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation means by the Government's being <hi>throughly ſettled.</hi> A Prince who is through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetled in his Throne, has God's Authority, and muſt be obeyed; but when is his Government throughly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</p>
                  <p>Now here it is, That men may impoſe upon themſelves if they will, and if they think it their Intereſt to do ſo; and may make as little or as much go to a through ſettlement, as they pleaſe;<note place="margin">No; they left that to d. <hi>Sherlock.</hi>
                     </note> for the <hi>Convocation</hi> has not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the bounds of it. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>The ſubmiſſion of the Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may be thought neceſſary to transfer a Legal Right; but the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the people, of it ſelf, is ſufficient to ſettle a Government; and when it is ſetled, then it is the Authority of God, whatever the Human Right be.</p>
                  <p>All Sovereign Powers, whoſe Power and Government is <hi>throughly ſetled,</hi> muſt be obeyed, whatever their Legal Right be; for they have the Authority of God. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>All Civil Power and Authority is from God; for he is the Supreme Lord of the World, and has the ſole Right to govern his Creatures; and therefore no man can have any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority but from God: This will be readily acknowledged by all, who believe, that there is a God, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41262:23"/>that he made and governs the World.</p>
                  <p>That Civil Power and Anthority is no otherwiſe from God, than as he gives this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority to ſome particular perſon or perſons,<note place="margin">But how does God give it him? Perhaps, as he gave you the Holy Ghoſt.</note> to govern others: For Authority be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to a perſon, and that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority which any perſon exerciſes, is not from God, which God never gave him: If he governs without receiving his <hi>Perſonal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> from God, he governs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God's Authority. <hi>p.</hi> 10.<note place="margin">O Sapientia</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are but three ways whereby God gives this Power and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to any perſons: Either by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or by an expreſs Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or by the diſpoſals of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>p.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>Providence is God's Government of the world by an inviſible influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and power, whereby he directs, determines, over-rules all Events to the accompliſhment of his own Will and Counſels. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Nor does it make any difference in this caſe, to diſtinguiſh between what God permits, and what he does; for this diſtinction does not relate to the Events of things, but to the wickedneſs of men. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>When it comes to action, he over-rules their wicked deſigns, to accompliſh his own Counſels and Decrees; and either diſappoints what they intended, or gives ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to them, when he can ſerve the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41262:24"/>ends of his Providence by their wickedneſs; and herein conſiſts the unſearchable Wiſdom of Providence, that God brings about his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, by the free Miniſtries of men: He permits men to do wickedly, but all Events which are for the good or evil of private men, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Societies, are ordered by him, as the Prophet declares, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>Shall there be evil in a city, and the Lord hath not done it? p.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>If the advancement to the Throne inveſts ſuch a Prince with God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then God gives him the Throne, and does not merely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to take it; for no man can take God's Authority, but it muſt be given. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>By what means ſoever any Prince aſcends the Throne, he is placed there by God, and receives his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from him. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes he ſuffers an aſpiring Prince to invade and conquer a Countrey; but he never ſuffers him to aſcend the Throne, but when he ſees fit to make him King. <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14.</p>
                  <p>All Kings are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rightful with reſpect to God;<note place="margin">So are all Clergy-men.</note> for thoſe are all rightful Kings, who are placed in the Throne by God, and it is impoſſible there ſhould be a wrong King, unleſs a man could make himſelf King, whether God will or no. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>The diſtinction then between a King <hi>de jure,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Doctor knows not when that Diſtinction was born, and when it died.</note> and a King <hi>de facto,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41262:24"/>only to Human Laws, which bind Subjects, but are not the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Rules and Meaſures of the Divine Providence. In Hereditary Kingdoms, he is a righful King, who has by Succeſſion a legal Right to the Crown; and he who has poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Crown, without a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right, is a King <hi>de facto;</hi> that is, is a King, but not by Law: Now Subjects are ſo tied up by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Kingdom, that they muſt not pull down or ſet up Kings contrary to the Laws of the Land; but God is not bound by Humane Laws,<note place="margin">Qui benè diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guit, benè docet.</note> but can make whom he pleaſe King, without regard to legal Rights; and when he does ſo, they are true, though not legal Kings,<note place="margin">I challenge the Doctor te quote any good Authority fer the Notion of a True King. A True and a Falſe Prophet we knew; but a True King is a Novelty.</note> if thoſe are true Kings who have God's Authority.</p>
                  <p>We can have but one King at a time; two rival and oppoſite Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cannot at the ſame time poſſeſs the ſame Throne, nor can Subjects be bound to two oppoſite and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Allegiances; for <hi>no man can Serve two maſters;</hi> and yet Allegiance is due to a King by the Laws of God, and to every King whoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects we are, that if we could have two Kings, we muſt have two Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giances.</p>
                  <p>He is our King who is ſettled in the Throne in the actual Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Sovereign Power; for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41262:25"/>
                     <hi>King</hi> is the Name of Power and Authority,<note place="margin">Under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivatur <hi>King?</hi>
                     </note> not of mere Right. He, who has a legal Right to the Crown, but has it not, ought by the Laws of the Land to be King, but is not: But he who is actually ſetled in the Adminiſtration of the Regal Power, is King, and has God's Authority, tho he have not a legal Right.</p>
                  <p>Allegiance is due only to the King; for Allegiance ſignifies all that Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which Subjects owe to their Ring, and therefore can be due to none but the King.</p>
                  <p>If then he who has the Legal Right, may not be our King, and he who has not, may; when any ſuch caſe happens, we muſt pay our Allegiance to him who is King, tho without a Legal Right; not to him who is not our King, tho it is his Right to be ſo: And the reaſor is very plain, becauſe Allegiance is due only to God's Authority, not to a bare Legal Title without God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and therefore muſt be paid to him who is inveſted with God's Authority, who is his Miniſter and Lieutenant; that is, to the Actual King, who is ſetled in the Throne, and has the Adminiſtration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But if this be ſo, what does a Legal Right ſignifie, if it do not command the Allegiance of Subjects?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer: It bars all other Human Claims: No other Prince
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41262:25"/>can challenge the Throne of Right; and Subjects are bound to maintain the Rights of ſuch a Prince, as far as they can; that is, againſt all Mankind; but not againſt God's diſpoſal of Crowns. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>We ſwear to maintain and defend his Right, and the Right of his Heirs; but yet we do not ſwear to keep them in the Throne, which may be impoſſible for us to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a proſperous Rebellion. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſeem to me, to be very plain <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> and to carry their own Evidence with them; and if this be true, it is a very plain Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Subjects in all the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Government.</p>
                  <p>The moſt that can be expected from them, according to the ſtricteſt Principles of Loyalty and Obedience,<note place="margin">lindx;</note> is to have no hand in ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions, or to oppoſe them as far as they can, and not to be haſty and forward in their Compliances; but when ſuch a Revolution is made, and they cannot help it; they muſt reverence and obey their New Prince, as inveſted with God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>There are different degrees of Settlement, and muſt neceſſarily be in ſuch new Governments, which ſeem to me to require different degrees of Submiſſion, or at leaſt to juſtify them, till it increaſes to ſuch a full, and plenary, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Poſſeſſion, as requires our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, as being notoriouſly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41262:26"/>and ſenſible to all that do not wink hard, and will not ſee it.</p>
                  <p>If the generality of the Nation ſubmit to ſuch a Prince, and place him on the Throne, and put the whole power of the Kingdom into his hands, though it may be, we cannot yet think the Providence of God has ſetled him in the Throne, while the diſpoſſeſſed Prince has alſo ſuch a formidable Power, as makes the Event very doubtful; yet if we think fit to continue in the Kingdom, under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Power of the New Prince, there are ſeveral Duties, which in reaſon we ought to pay him.</p>
                  <p>As, To live quietly and peaceably under his Government, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or ſwear, or give any other ſecurity that we will do ſo, if it be demanded: It is reaſonable we ſhould do ſo, if we think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to live under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Government; this all men do in an Enemy's Quarters, and no man blames them for it.</p>
                  <p>We muſt pay Taxes to them; for theſe are due to the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Government, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves; <hi>For this cauſe pay ye tribute alſo, for they are the miniſters of God, attending continually on this very thing,</hi> Rom. 13. 6. And if we owe our ſecure poſſeſſion of our Eſtates to the protection of Government, let the Government be what it will, we ought to pay for it.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41262:26"/>
                  <p>We muſt give the Title of King to ſuch a Prince, when we live in the Country where he is owned for King; for beſides that, it is a piece of good manners (which is the leaſt thing we can owe to him, under whoſe Government we live) he is indeed King, while he adminiſters the Regal Power, though we may not think him ſo well ſetled in his Government, as to all intents and purpoſes to own him for our King.</p>
                  <p>Nay, we muſt pray for him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name and Title of King, for we are bound to pray for all who are in Authority; and that Prince is, who has the whole Government in his hands, and has power to do a great deal of hurt, or a great of good; and this is ſo far from being a fault, that it is a duty, while we take care to do it in ſuch terms,<note place="margin">lindx;</note> as to not pray againſt the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed Prince.</p>
                  <p>Thus far I think the doubtful poſſeſſion of the Throne obliges us, and it were very happy if no more were required in the beginnings of ſuch a new Government; but when, beſides the poſſeſſion of the Throne, the Power of the diſpoſſeſſed Prince is broken, and no viſible proſpect of his recovering his Throne again; nay, if it be viſible that he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recover his Throne again, but by making a new Conqueſt of the Nation by Foreigners, who will be our Maſters, if they conquer,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41262:27"/>and no very gentle ones neither; we may then look upon the new Prince as advanced and ſetled by God in his Throne, and therefore ſuch a King, as we owe an entire Obedience and Allegiance to.</p>
                  <p>For we muſt not take the conſideration of Right into the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Government;<note place="margin">No, have a care of that.</note> for a Prince may be ſetled in his Throne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Legal Right; and when he is ſo, God has made him our King, and requires our Obedience. <hi>p.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>The Scripture has given us no Directions in this Caſe, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and pay all the Obedience of Subjects to the preſent Powers. It makes no diſtinction, that ever I could find, between Rightful Kings and Uſurpers, between Kings whom we muſt, and whom we muſt not obey; but the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule is, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers, for all power is of God.</hi> p. 18.</p>
                  <p>To ſay the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here ſpeaks of Lawful Power, is <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> for there is no Evidence of it: The Criticiſm between <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> will not do; for they both ſignify the ſame thing in Scripture, either Force and Power, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſays, <hi>All power is of God,</hi> there is no reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine this <hi>to the Legal Powers,</hi> unleſs it were evidently the Doctrine of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41262:27"/>Scripture, that <hi>uſurped Powers are not of God,</hi> which is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, that the contrary is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; <hi>that the moſt high ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will,</hi> 4 Dan. 17. which is ſpoke with reference to the <hi>four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies,</hi> which were all as manifeſt Uſurpations as ever were in the World, and yet ſet up by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and Counſel of God, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by a prophetick Spirit: and whoever will confine the Power and Authority of God,<note place="margin">Wiſdom will die with this man!</note> 
                     <hi>in changing Times and Seaſons, in removing Kings, and ſetting up Kings,</hi> to Humane Laws, ought not to be diſputed with. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>This I'm ſure, The only dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Scripture is to ſubmit to thoſe who are in Authority, who are in the actual adminiſtration of Government, to reverence and obey them, to pray for them, to pay Tribute to them, <hi>as God's Miniſters, attending continually upon this very thing,</hi> and not to reſiſt them; but there is not the leaſt notice given us of any kind of Duty owing, or to be paid, to a Prince out of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and removed from the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Government, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Right may be. <hi>p.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p>The Prophecy of the <hi>Four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> is not yet at an end; for under the <hi>fourth</hi> Monarchy the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to be ſet up, and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was to appear, and the increaſe and deſtruction
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41262:28"/>of the Kingdom of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is to be accompliſhed by great Changes and Revolutions in Humane Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; and when God has declared, that he will change Times and Seaſons, remove Kings, and ſet up Kings, to accompliſh his own wiſe Counſels, it juſtifies our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and therefore innocent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances with ſuch Revolutions, as much as if we were expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do ſo, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> This a man may ſay without Enthuſiaſm, or pretending to underſtand all the Propheſies of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and to apply them to their particular events; for without that, we certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, that all the great Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the World are intended by God to ſerve thoſe great Ends; and when God will overturn King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Empires, remove, and ſet up Kings, as he ſees will beſt ſerve the accompliſhment of his own Counſels and Decrees, it is very hard, if Subjects muſt not quietly ſubmit to ſuch Revolutions: we muſt not, contrary to our ſworn Duty and Allegiance, promote ſuch Revolutions,<note place="margin">No, tho we be upon the point of loſing our Lan's and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</note> upon a pretence of fulfilling Propheſies; but when they are made and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, we ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them.</p>
                  <p>We have no direction in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture at all about making or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making Kings, or reſtoring a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed Prince to his Throne again; and all the Commands we have in Scripture about Obedience and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41262:28"/>to Government, manifeſtly reſpects the preſent Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Powers,<note place="margin">Let God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty turn Kingdoms topſie turvie, as he pleaſes, the Doctor will always fall upon his feet.</note> without any diſtinction between right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Uſurped Powers; it ſeems therefore plainly to determin this Queſtion on the ſide of the preſent Powers. <hi>p.</hi> 22, 23.</p>
                  <p>If the Choice and Conſent of the people makes a Prince, then no man is a Subject, but he who conſents to be ſo; for the Major Vote cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my conſent, unleſs I pleaſe; that is the effect of Law and Compact, or Force, not of Nature. If Subjects give their Prince Authority, they may take it away again, if they pleaſe; there can be no irreſiſtible Authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the people; for if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority be wholly derived from them, who ſhall hinder them from taking it away, when they ſee fit?<note place="margin">If a man gives me a pair of Gloves, who ſhall hinder him from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way again, when he ſees fit?</note> Upon theſe Principles, there can be no Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy; one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration can only chuſe for themſelves, their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity having as much Right to choſe as they had. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</p>
                  <p>I cannot ſee where to fix the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Government, but in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, who either by the choice of the major or ſtronger part of the people, or by Conqueſt, or by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and the long ſucceſſive conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of power, or by Human Laws, gives a Prince and his Family poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Throne, which is a good Title againſt all Humane Claims, and requires the Obedience and Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41262:29"/>of Subjects as long as God is pleaſed to continue him and his Family in the Throne; but it is no Title againſt God, if he pleaſe to advance another Prince. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</p>
                  <p>To ſay that God ſets up no Prince, who aſcends the Throne without a Humane and Legal Right, is to ſay, that ſome Kings are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and others ſet up, but not by God; which is a direct contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to Scripture; it is to ſay, That the <hi>Four Monarchies</hi> were not ſet up by God, becauſe they all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by Violence and Uſurpation: It is to ſay, That God, as well as men, is confined by Humane Laws, in making Kings: It is to ſay, That the Right of Government is not derived from God, without the conſent of the people; for if God can't make a King without the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or againſt their conſent decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by their Laws, the Authority muſt be derived from the people, not from God; or at leaſt if it be God's Authority, yet God can't give it himſelf without the people, nor otherwiſe than they have dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him by their Laws.</p>
                  <p>This is all very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd.<note place="margin">So's all the reſt of your Book, Sir.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Providence of God removes Kings, and ſets up Kings, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters no Legal Right, nor forbids thoſe who are diſpoſſeſſed of them, to recover their Right, when they can. While ſuch a Prince is in the Throne, it is a declaration of God's Will, that he ſhall Reign for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41262:29"/>ſome time, longer or ſhorter, as God pleaſes; and that is an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Subjects to ſubmit and obey; for Submiſſion is owing only to God's Authority; but that one Prince is at preſent placed in the Throne, and the other removed out of it, does not prove, that it is God's Will it ſhould always be ſo, and therefore does not diveſt the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed Prince to recover his Legal Right: <hi>A Legal and Succeſſive Right is the ordinary way whereby the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God advances Princes to an Hereditary Throne: And this bars all other humane Claims, but yet God may give the Throne to another, if he pleaſes; and this does not deſtroy the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right of the diſpoſſeſſed Prince,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">lindx;</note> 
                     <hi>nor hinder him from claiming it, when he finds his opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> p. 26.</p>
                  <p>It is a great Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,<note place="margin">Why, 'tis a Legal Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but it has not the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God.</note> which I am not Lawyer enough to decide; Whether a Commiſſion granted by a King out of Poſſeſſion, be a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Commiſſion? <hi>p.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <p>Oaths oblige every particular man to do no injury to the King's Perſon or Crown, not to enter into Plots and Conſpiracies againſt him; and as for actual defence, chearfully to venture his Life and Fortunes with his Fellow-ſubjects to preſerve the King. But in caſe the great Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Nation abſolve themſelves from theſe Oaths, and depoſe their King, and drive him out of his Kingdom, and ſet up another Prince
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41262:30"/>in his room, it is worth conſidering, Whether ſome private men, i: may be but a little handful, are ſtill bound by their Oath, to make ſome weak and dangerous attempts, and to fight for their King againſt their Countrey; certainly this was not the intention of the Oath; for it is a National, not a private Defence, we ſwear; and therefore a <hi>general revolt of a Nation, tho it ſhould be wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unjuſtifiable, yet it ſeems to excuſe thoſe, who had neither hand nor heart in it, from their ſworn defence of the King's Perſon and Crown, and to make their compliane with the National Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, innocent and neceſſary.</hi> For an Oath to fight for the King, does not oblige us to fight againſt our Countrey, which is as unnatural, as to fight againſt our King. The ſum is this; God, when he ſees fit, can remove Kings, or ſet up Kings, without any regard to humane Right, as being the Sovereign Lord of the World, who rules in the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth them to whomſoever he will; but <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> in ſetting up, or removing Kings, muſt have regard to Legal Right; and if they pull down a rightful King, and ſet up a King without right, <hi>(unleſs the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government in ſome caſes ſhould allow it)</hi> greatly ſin in it, eſpecially when they have ſworn the defence of the Legal Right, and Legal Succeſſion; but the Duty and Allegiance of Subjects does not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately reſpect Right, but the actual Adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41262:30"/>when there is a ſetled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a Nation; for that is God's Authority, which much be obeyed; no man muſt ſwear away this, no more than any other part of his Duty; and no man does ſwear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way this by the Oath of Allegiance, as I have already ſhown. <hi>p.</hi> 31, 32.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But have not Pyrates and Robbers as good a Title to my Purſe, as an Uſurper has to the Crown, which he ſeizes by as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt force and violence?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Outrages of Thieves and Pyrates are very impertinently alledged in this Cauſe. They have force and violence, which every man muſt ſubmit to, when he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help it; but Sovereign Power is God's Authority, tho Princes may be advanced to it by no honeſter means than Thieves take a Purſe, or break open my Houſe, and take my Money or Goods. The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Four Monarchies were no better, and yet their Power was God's. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</p>
                  <p>This Doctrine of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Allegiance to the preſent Powers,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14.</note> is founded on the ſame Principle with the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive-Obedience,</hi> and therefore both muſt be true, or both falſe; for it is founded on this Principle, That God makes Kings, and inveſts them with his Authority, which equally proves, That all Kings, who have received a Sovereign Authority from God,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41262:31"/>and are in the actual adminiſtration of it (which is the only evidence we have, that they have received it from God) muſt be obeyed, and muſt not be reſiſted. <hi>Set aſide this Principle, That all Sovereign Princes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Authority from God, and I grant that Non-Reſiſtance is Nonſenſe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>for there is no other irreſiſtible Authority, but that of God. p.</hi> 36.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Principles anſwer all the ends of Government, both for the ſecurity of the Prince and Subjects; and that is a good Argument to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them true.</p>
                  <p>A Prince who is in Poſſeſſion, is ſecured in Poſſeſſion by them, (as far as any Principles can ſecure him) againſt all Attempts of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who muſt reverence God's Authority in him; and ſubmit to him without Reſiſtance, tho they are ill uſed.</p>
                  <p>They will not indeed ſerve the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of Government, to remove one King, and ſet up another; and if they would, Princes, might be jealous of them; for whatever Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they might do them at one turn, they might do them as great Diſſervice at another: The Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Government are not the Subjects Duty, but God's Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and therefore it is not likely that he has preſcribed any certain Rules or Methods for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning and changing Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he keeps in his own hands, and which when he ſees fit to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41262:31"/>do it, he never wants ways and means of doing.</p>
                  <p>But when any Prince is ſetled in the Throne, by what means ſoever it be, theſe Principles put an end to all diſputes of Right and Title, and bind his Subjects to him by Duty and Conſcience, and a Reverence of God's Authority; which is the faſteſt hold he can poſſibly have of them;<note place="margin">No; Interest is the faſteſt hold in theſe caſes.</note> for thoſe whom Religion will not bind, nothing but Force can.</p>
                  <p>And therefore theſe are the only principles which in ſuch Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can make Government eaſie both to Prince and People; and if Government muſt be preſerved in all Revolutions, thoſe are the beſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which are moſt for the eaſe and ſafety of it.</p>
                  <p>But on the other hand, ſuch an immoveable and unalterable Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, as is thought due only to a Legal Right and Title, and muſt be paid to none, but to a Legal and Rightful Prince, ſerves no ends of Government at all; but overturns all Government, when ſuch a Prince is diſpoſſeſſed of his Throne, how long ſoever he continue diſpoſſeſſed: And what long <hi>Inter-regnums</hi> may this occaſion, to the diſſolution of Human Societies? <hi>p.</hi> 43, 44.</p>
                  <p>I cannot indeed think (neither do I believe, that any body elſe does) that for a King to leave his Crown and Government in a fright, is in all caſes neceſſarily to be interpreted ſuch an Abdication as is equivalent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41262:32"/>to a voluntary Reſignation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he renounces all future Right and Claim to it. But if he have reduced himſelf to ſuch a ſtate, that he is forced for his own preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to leave his Kingdom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; it is plain, that in ſome ſenſe he leaves his Throne vacant too; that is, there is no body in it, no body in the actual Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government.</p>
                  <p>Thus far I think Subjects may be very guiltleſs who do not drive the King away, but only ſuffer him quietly to eſcape out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; for this is no <hi>Rebellion,</hi> no <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> but only <hi>Non-Aſſiſtance,</hi> which may be very innocent; for there are ſome caſes wherein Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not bound to aſſiſt their Prince; and if ever there were ſuch a Caſe, this was it.</p>
                  <p>What then ſhall Subjects do, when the King is gone, and the Government Diſſolved, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple left in the Hands of another Prince, without any Reaſon, or any Authority, or any formed Power, to oppoſe him? The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment muſt be Adminiſtred by ſome-body, unleſs we can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that the Rabble ſhould govern.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>I ſhall not meddle with that Interval between the going away of the King, and the Prince's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Throne;</hi> but only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him as placed in the Throne,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41262:32"/>and ſetled there. And now we can find no alteration in the Ancient government of the Nation, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the exchange of perſons; and all things concur to make this a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry advantageous and acceptable Change, excepting ſuch difficulties, as uſually accompany ſuch Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>p.</hi> 49, 50.</p>
                  <p>Legal Rights muſt be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a Legal Authority; and there is no Authority can take cognizance of the Titles and Claims of Princes, and the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the Crown, but the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Realm: <hi>They indeed are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to take notice of the legal Deſcent of the Crown;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>and if through miſtake, or any other cauſe, they ſet the Crown upon a wrong Head, they muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for it;</hi> but private Subjects, who have no legal Cognizance of the matter, are bound by no Law, that I know of, to diſown a King whom the <hi>Eſtates</hi> have owned, though they ſhould think the Right is in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <hi>p.</hi> 52, 53.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hitherto have been diſplayed the Principles of ſome of our heavenly Guides, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to our Preſent Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41262:33"/>
                  <head>The <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the whole matter take in the Words of a Worthy Divine, lately delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a <hi>Sermon</hi> before the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> viz.</head>
                  <p>WE may ſafely conclude from the late Deliverance which we have found, and the Succeſs wherewith it has been attended ſince, 1. That God has ſignally ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted his favour to this our <hi>Church.</hi> And 2. That the <hi>King</hi> is the Inſtrument whereby he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd this Favour on us. And from hence there ariſes a twofold Duty upon us:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we ſhould have a regard and reverence for the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That we ſhould pay Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Obedience to the King. And,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How great a veneration and eſteem do we juſtly owe to that Church, which firſt reſcued us from the Tyranny of the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke; recovered the pure Word of God from their uſurpation and diſguiſe, and inſtated us in the true light of the Goſpel! A Church, which for the purity of her Faith, and the Regularity of her Inſtitution, has ever ſince ſtood the Envy, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the brunt of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and has ſo many miraculous deliverances to ſhew, that God has eſpouſed her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41262:33"/>Cauſe. We have heard with out Ears, and our Fathers have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd unto us, the Wonders which he did for her in their days, <hi>and our own eyes alſo have ſeen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God.</hi> How he reſcued us from an implacable ravenous Herd of Men, who had nothing but numbers to entitle them to a Catholick Church, and with thoſe numbers they deſign'd to over-power the Truth; with thoſe Wolves they thought to have worry'd this little Flock: Againſt us alone they bent all their Rage, and whet their Teeth in the late unhappy Reign; and when their ſmall ſtock of Arguments was ſpent, they prepar'd for another kind of onſet. But <hi>God deliver'd us from all the expectation of the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, and ſhew'd, that it was not their Church, but ours, that is founded upon that Rock: And I wiſh all they that are ſtill proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to overturn it, would for their own ſecurity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this,<note place="margin">What do you think of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well?</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That no weapon ever proſper'd yet, that has been lifted up againſt it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now for any of us to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>the honeſty</hi> of our Mother-Church, which we have ſeen at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by ſo many unqueſtionable proofs, by all the demonſtration that the nature of the thing will bear, muſt be ſomething more than Ignorance, ſomething that I am loath to name. <hi>To forſake this guide of our youth, who never deſerted us in any times of difficulty, never conſulted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41262:34"/>her own ſafety when ſhe ſaw her Sons in danger,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>but boldly oppos'd every Enemy, and ſtood in every breach,</hi> for us, I ſay, to deſert her upon any ſcore, is ſuch vile ingratitude, as hardly can be parallel'd, but can never be excus'd. <hi>What iniquity have your fathers found in me,</hi> ſaid God, <hi>that ye ſhould forfake me, and follow after other gods.</hi> A very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Expoſtulation! a moſt patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Complaint!</p>
                  <p>And the ſame thing may be ſaid in behalf of our native Church. What is there in this our way of Worſhip that can juſtly give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence? What is there in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that the godlieſt Man can ſcruple, or the wiſeſt Man can mend? What Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Prayer can be made, for any Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,<note place="margin">A Prayer for honeſt Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would do well to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> or any Grant, of which our humane nature ſtands in need, that is not daily and decently offer'd up to God from this our Houſe of Prayer? What Portion of God's Holy Word is there that is not here duly read, and, I hope, faithfully explain'd unto you? What Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine have we conceal'd from you, or when have we taught you <hi>for Doctrine, the Commandments of men?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">When ye coin'd new Articles of Faith, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded them upon us <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
                     </note> Where have we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded you of that which is the Word of God, or impos'd upon you that which is not?</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41262:34"/>
                  <p>If any of theſe Charges can be made out, then we will willingly bear the blame till there is a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; but if they cannot be prov'd upon us, as I am certain that they can't; if our Church has conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharg'd the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a careful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">God knows they can.</note> then well may ſhe expect from us the obedience of Sons; or elſe cry out upon our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>What iniquity have you or your fathers found in me?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the mean while, I wiſh every man would conſcientiouſly conſider this, That a needleſs Separation is very far from being an indifferent harmleſs thing; and therefore they whoſe Conſciences will give them leave to communicate with us at ſome times, I know not how they can excuſe themſelves for not doing always ſo; for certainly Union is ſo poſitive a Command of God, and the want of it is of ſo pernicious conſequence to the Souls of men, that nothing but abſolute neceſſity can give us a diſpenſation; nothing can juſtify us for breaking the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, but when the terms of Communion are utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful; if any man thinks that our terms are ſuch, they have their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and we have ours; and ſo I hope there may be Charity, although there is not Union amongſt us; and therefore leaving every man freely to his own way, as he will anſwer it to God, who cannot be deceiv'd, as well as to his own Conſcience, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41262:35"/>can; let us proceed to the laſt thing propos'd, wherein I hope we do all agree; and that is, in paying Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Obedience to our Sovereign;<note place="margin">Civil and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd.</note> and that not only upon a Civil, but alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sacred account; not <hi>only for wrath, but for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Kings are the only Perſons upon Earth unto whom God has given an immediate delegation of his Authority; whom to obey, is to obey his Ordinance; and whom to reſiſt, is to reſiſt his Power: And whoſoever denies Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be a religious duty, takes away from the King the faireſt Jewel in his Crown, and the ſtrongeſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs in his Dominion.</p>
                  <p>But this is a Doctrine that has been ſo frequently diſcuſs'd of late; ſo learnedly demonſtrated, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably eſtabliſh'd amongſt us that there is no need to inſiſt upon it now. Only give me leave to ſay, That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the unreaſonable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of gainſaying men, yet <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> always was, and I hope always will be, the Doctrine and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I am ſure <hi>'tis a Doctrine of which no Church need to be aſham'd, and no King can be afraid:</hi> And to this I ſhall only add, That all that Obedience which the Scripture requires us to pay unto the King, we muſt now look upon as devolv'd upon Their preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, and properly belonging to Their Claim. <hi>The powers that are</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are ordained of God;</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account they juſtly challenge
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41262:35"/>our ſubmiſſion. And in this point, tho I muſt not ſay with St. <hi>Paul, that I think I have the Spirit of God;</hi> yet I dare ſay,<note place="margin">You mean of a great many of your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of your Church, you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not.</note> that <hi>I have the Spirit of that Church in which I was born and bred.</hi> And I dare ſay no more: For Crowns and Scepters are very nice, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things; ſomething a-kin to the Ark of God; they muſt be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Ceremony: and tho we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them with never ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, yet by an unskilful touch, we may eaſily offend; and 'tis a treſpaſs upon Majeſty to come too near it.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> the Lords and Commons ordered, That His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt gracious Anſwer this day, be added to the Engroſſed Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Parchment, to be enroll'd in Parliament and Chancery; which is as followeth.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THis is certainly the greateſt proof of the Truſt you have in Us, that can be given, which is the thing that maketh Us value it the more; and We thankfully accept what you have offered. And as I had no other intention in my coming hither, than to preſerve Your Religion, Laws and Liberties: So you may be ſure, that I ſhall endeavour to ſupport them, and ſhall be willing to concur in any thing that ſhall be for the Good of the Kingdom, and to do all that is in my Power to advance the Welfare and Glory of the Nation.</p>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:41262:36"/>
                        <p>Thus ended that ſtupendious Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> which we have ſo lately ſeen; to the great Joy of the Generality of the Proteſtants of <hi>Europe,</hi> and of many of the Catholick Princes and States, who were at laſt convinced, that the attempting to force <hi>England,</hi> to return under the Obedience of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> in the preſent conjuncture of Affairs, would certainly end in the Ruin of this potent Kingdom; and whilſt it was doing, the preſent <hi>French</hi> King would poſſeſs himſelf of the Remainder of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands,</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and perhaps of the Electorates of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne, Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Triers,</hi> a great part of which he hath actually ſeized, whilſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was thus gloriouſly aſſerting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty.</p>
                        <p>The Convention having declared the King and Queen, as aforeſaid, proceeded to Declare themſelves a Parliament, to ſettle the Coronation-Oath, to Repeal that Clauſe in an Oath and Declaration, <hi>That it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to Take up Arms againſt the King, or thoſe Commiſſioned by him;</hi> To revive the Adminiſtration of the Law, which had been interrupted; and therein they particularly Enact, That Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Offences committed betwixt the 11th. of <hi>December,</hi> and the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1688, ſhould run, <hi>Contra Pacem Regni.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And by the Firſt Act of this preſent Parliament, <hi>The Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, did Recognize and Acknowledge, That their Majeſties were, and of Kight ought to be, by the Laws of this Realm, their Sovereign Liege Lord and Lady, King and Queen of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And by the ſame Act it was enacted, <hi>That all and ſingular the Acts made and Enacted by the laſt Parliament, were and are the Laws and Statutes of this Kingdom, and as ſuch ought to be reputed, taken, and obeyed by all the people of the ſame.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <hi>God ſave King</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and Queen</hi> MARY.</closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:36"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TRuth brought to light by Time; or the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Tranſactions of the firſt fourteen Years of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign. <hi>The ſecond Edition, with Additions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New, Plain, Short, and Compleat <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grammer; whereby the Learned may attain in few Months to Speak and Write <hi>French</hi> Correctly, as they do now in the Court of <hi>France.</hi> And wherein all that is Dark, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and deficient in other <hi>Grammers,</hi> is Plain, Short and Methodically Supplied. Alſo very uſeful to ſtrangers, that are deſirons to learn the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue: For whoſe ſake is addded a Short, but very Exact <hi>Engliſh Grammer. The Second Edition. By</hi> Peter Berault.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Devout Chriſtian's</hi> Preparation for holy Dying. Conſiſting of Ejaculations, Prayers, Meditations and Hymns, adopted to the ſeveral States and Conditions of this Life. And on the four laſt things, <hi>viz. Death, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Victoriae Anglicanae;</hi> being an Hiſtorical Collection of all the Memorable and Stupendious Victories obtain'd by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> both by Sea and Land, ſince the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt. <hi>viz.</hi> The Battle, 1. Between. K. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry II.</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Normandy.</hi> 2. At <hi>Morleis.</hi> 3. At the Reſcue of <hi>Calice.</hi> 4. At <hi>Poicters.</hi> 5. At <hi>Creſſey.</hi> 6. At <hi>Agincourt.</hi> 7. At the mouth of the River <hi>Seine.</hi> 8. At <hi>Vernoil.</hi> 9. At <hi>Cravant.</hi> 10. At the Relief of <hi>Orleance,</hi> with the great Actions of the <hi>Lord Salisbury</hi> and <hi>Talbot.</hi> 11. Of <hi>Spurrs.</hi> Dedicated to all the Commiſſion'd Officers of the Maritime and Land Forces. <hi>Price ſtitcht</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41262:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathematical Magick:</hi> Or, the Wonders that may be Performed by Mechanical Geometry. In Two Books. Concerning mechanical Powers, Motions. Being one of the moſt Eaſie, Pleaſant, Uſeful, (and yet moſt neglected) part of Mathematicks. Not before treated of in this Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. By <hi>J. Wilkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> The Fourth Edition.</p>
            <p>The Memoirs of Monſieur <hi>Deagant:</hi> Containing the moſt Secret Tranſactions and Affairs of <hi>France,</hi> from the Death of <hi>Henry IV.</hi> till the beginning of the Miniſtry of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>de Richlieu.</hi> To which is added, a particular Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Embrun's</hi> Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotiation for the advancement of the Roman-Catholick Religion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham's</hi> Letters to the ſaid Archbiſhop about the Progreſs of that Affair: Which happen'd the laſt Years of King <hi>James I.</hi> his Reign. Faithfully tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>A True Relation of the Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners of War; being a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of their Travels from <hi>Dinant</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> and back again. With a Deſcription of the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation and Fortifications of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Diſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Faithfully and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Performed by <hi>Richard Strutton,</hi> being an Eye-witneſs, and a Fellow-Sufferer.</p>
            <p>The State of <hi>Savoy:</hi> In which a full and diſtinct: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is given of the Perſecution of the Proteſtants in the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> by means of the <hi>French</hi> Councils: As alſo of the Unreaſonable Conditions and Demands that the <hi>French</hi> King would have put on the Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> And of the juſt Cauſes and Motives that induced that Duke to break off from the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, and join with the <hi>Confederates:</hi> Together with the moſt memorable Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that have ſince hapned there: As alſo the true Copies of all the Letters and Diſpatches that have paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
